<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-03T23:39:19+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/feed.xml</id><title type="html">infoBAG</title><entry><title type="html">BIOS settings for improved performance on GMKtec G5 (Intel N97)</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/bios-settings-for-improved-performance-on-gmktec-g5-intel-n97/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BIOS settings for improved performance on GMKtec G5 (Intel N97)" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T16:57:38+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/bios-settings-for-improved-performance-on-gmktec-g5-intel-n97</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/bios-settings-for-improved-performance-on-gmktec-g5-intel-n97/"><![CDATA[<p>Tuning BIOS settings can potentially enhance performance, but it requires careful adjustments and testing, especially on compact systems like the GMKtec G5 with its Intel N97 processor [Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[1]]. Pushing settings too aggressively can lead to instability, overheating, or reduced component lifespan.</p>

<p><strong>Important Disclaimers &amp; Prerequisites:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Risk:</strong> Modifying BIOS settings beyond defaults carries risks. Proceed at your own discretion. Instability might require resetting the BIOS (CMOS clear, possibly via jumper shorting [User Context]).</li>
  <li><strong>Cooling:</strong> These recommendations assume your GMKtec G5 has adequate cooling. Monitor temperatures closely (e.g., using HWiNFO64) during stress tests. If CPU temperatures consistently exceed LEFTPAREN85-90^\circ CRIGHTPAREN, you <em>must</em> relax power limits, voltage offsets, or clock speeds.</li>
  <li><strong>BIOS Version:</strong> Ensure you have the latest GMKtec G5 BIOS installed. Some features, like the 1200 MHz iGPU clock, require specific updates (e.g., build dated May 22 2024 or later [User Context, optimal BIOS settings GMKtec G5 N97 performance: organic[2], optimal BIOS settings GMKtec G5 N97 performance: organic[4]]). Access the BIOS by pressing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Esc</code> during startup [User Context].</li>
  <li><strong>Incremental Changes:</strong> Apply changes incrementally, testing stability (e.g., with Cinebench R23, Prime95 Small FFTs, 3DMark) after each significant adjustment before proceeding.</li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> These settings aim for higher sustained performance and responsiveness, balancing clock speeds with the N97’s thermal and power constraints (12W base TDP [Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[1], Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[9]]). They prioritize enabling dynamic boosting mechanisms effectively.</li>
</ol>

<p>Here are the recommended BIOS settings, categorized by section, targeting improved performance on your GMKtec G5 (Intel N97):</p>

<p><strong>1. CPU Settings (Advanced → CPU Configuration)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Turbo Ratio Limits / Performance CPU Ratio:</strong> Ensure Turbo Boost is <strong>Enabled</strong>. If manual ratio control is available, you can <em>try</em> setting the max ratio to <strong>36</strong> (for the N97’s 3.6 GHz max boost [Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[1]]). Monitor stability and thermals closely if setting manually. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Auto</code> is safer.</li>
  <li><strong>C-State Control / CPU C-State Support:</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong>. While disabling C-states is common advice for minimizing latency on high-end desktops, a user report for this specific GMKtec G5 N97 suggests enabling C-states is <em>necessary</em> for the CPU to properly reach its turbo boost frequencies [optimal BIOS settings GMKtec G5 N97 performance: organic[1]]. Enabling them allows the CPU to enter low-power states when idle, reducing heat and power consumption, which can paradoxically help sustain boost clocks longer under load in a thermally constrained system.</li>
  <li><strong>Intel SpeedStep Technology (EIST):</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong>. This allows the CPU to dynamically adjust its clock speed based on load, which is essential for managing power consumption and heat. Disabling it forces high clocks constantly, likely leading to faster thermal throttling and potentially <em>lower</em> sustained performance.</li>
  <li><strong>Hyper-Threading Technology:</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong> (The N97 is 4 Cores / 4 Threads, so this specific setting might not be present or applicable as it doesn’t have Hyper-Threading like Core i-series CPUs, but ensure core enablement reflects 4C/4T).</li>
  <li><strong>CPU Voltage Offset:</strong> Start with <strong>Auto</strong> or <strong>0 mV</strong>. If experiencing instability at target clocks/power limits, <em>or</em> if trying to slightly <em>reduce</em> heat, you can cautiously experiment with small offsets <em>if the BIOS permits</em>. Try LEFTPAREN \pm 10 RIGHTPARENmV to LEFTPAREN \pm 25 RIGHTPARENmV increments, testing thoroughly after each change. Positive offset LEFTPAREN (+) RIGHTPAREN <em>might</em> improve stability at higher clocks but increases heat/power. Negative offset LEFTPAREN (-) RIGHTPAREN reduces heat/power but might reduce stability. Granularity might differ from the “±100 MHz” mentioned for frequency [User Context].</li>
  <li><strong>Power Limits (PL1/PL2):</strong> This is critical for performance in thermally limited systems.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Package Power Limit 2 (PL2):</strong> Set to <strong>15W</strong> to <strong>18W</strong>. This defines the short-term boost power. Start lower (15W) [Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[2]] and increase only if thermals remain under control during bursts (e.g., application loading, short benchmarks).</li>
      <li><strong>Package Power Limit 1 (PL1):</strong> Set to <strong>12W</strong> to <strong>15W</strong>. This defines the sustained power limit. Matching it to the N97’s base TDP (12W [Intel Alder Lake-N N97 CPU BIOS optimization: organic[1]]) is the safest start. You can try increasing towards your stable PL2 value (e.g., 15W) if cooling allows sustained operation without throttling.</li>
      <li><strong>PL1 Time Window (Tau):</strong> Leave at <strong>Auto</strong> or <strong>28 seconds</strong> if configurable. This determines how long PL2 can be maintained before dropping to PL1.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>AVX Ratio Offset:</strong> Set to <strong>0</strong> or <strong>Auto</strong>. Setting 0 ensures AVX workloads run at the full target frequency, but monitor heat as AVX instructions are power-hungry.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Memory (Advanced → DRAM Configuration)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>XMP Profile:</strong> Select <strong>Profile 1</strong> (or the highest available profile) if using compatible DDR5-4800 SODIMMs [User Context] to automatically configure optimal frequency, timings, and voltage (likely 1.1V or slightly higher per XMP spec).</li>
  <li><strong>Memory Frequency:</strong> Ensure it’s running at <strong>DDR5-4800 MHz</strong>. If XMP doesn’t work or isn’t available, set this manually.</li>
  <li><strong>Timings (tCL, tRCD, tRP, tRAS):</strong> Leave on <strong>Auto</strong> or XMP defaults unless you are experienced with manual memory tuning. Tighter timings offer minor gains but risk instability.</li>
  <li><strong>Command Rate:</strong> <strong>Auto</strong> (often defaults to 2T for compatibility, 1T might be slightly faster but harder to stabilize).</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>3. Integrated GPU (Advanced → North Bridge or System Agent Configuration)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>iGPU Maximum Frequency Override:</strong> If available and you have the updated BIOS, set to <strong>1200 MHz</strong> [User Context, optimal BIOS settings GMKtec G5 N97 performance: organic[2]]. Leave on Auto if unsure or using an older BIOS.</li>
  <li><strong>DVMT Pre-Allocated:</strong> <strong>Auto</strong> or <strong>256MB</strong>. The operating system will dynamically allocate more memory as needed (up to half the system RAM typically). Setting higher pre-allocation (e.g., 512MB) is usually unnecessary unless specific applications demand it.</li>
  <li><strong>iGPU Power Limit:</strong> If tunable, set to the <strong>Maximum</strong> available setting or leave on <strong>Auto</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Storage &amp; I/O (Advanced → Onboard Devices Configuration)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>M.2 PCIe Link Speed:</strong> Ensure set to <strong>Gen4 x4</strong> for maximum NVMe SSD performance [User Context].</li>
  <li><strong>SATA Mode Selection:</strong> <strong>AHCI</strong> (unless you specifically set up a RAID array, which is unlikely in this mini-PC).</li>
  <li><strong>USB Port Configuration:</strong> Leave <strong>Enabled</strong> unless you have a specific reason to disable a port. Disabling unused USB 2.0 ports offers negligible performance benefits [Previous Response Analysis].</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>5. Boot (Boot → Boot Configuration)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Fast Boot / Quick Boot:</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong> to speed up POST [User Context].</li>
  <li><strong>CSM (Compatibility Support Module):</strong> <strong>Disabled</strong> for pure UEFI boot (required for features like Secure Boot and generally preferred for modern OSes).</li>
  <li><strong>Boot Order:</strong> Set your primary OS drive (NVMe SSD) as the first boot device.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>6. Security &amp; Virtualization (Security → Security Settings)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>TPM Device Selection / Security Device Support:</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong> (Set to Intel PTT - Platform Trust Technology [User Context]) for Windows 11 compatibility and security features like BitLocker.</li>
  <li><strong>Intel Virtualization Technology (VT-x):</strong> <strong>Enabled</strong> [User Context]. Disabling this offers minimal (if any) power savings [Previous Response Analysis] and prevents running virtual machines or WSL2/Hyper-V. Leave it enabled unless you are certain you will <em>never</em> need virtualization.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>7. Power Management (Advanced → ACPI Settings or Platform Power Management) (Continued)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>ACPI Sleep State / Standby Mode:</strong> Leave at <strong>Auto</strong> or enable <strong>S3 (Suspend to RAM)</strong> or <strong>Modern Standby/S0ix Low Power Idle</strong> if available and desired [User Context]. Disabling sleep states hinders power saving during idle or sleep periods and often has no benefit for peak performance. While disabling might slightly speed up wake times, it comes at the cost of higher power drain when the system is supposed to be sleeping. Keep defaults unless you encounter specific issues with sleep/wake functionality.</li>
  <li><strong>Wake-on-LAN (WOL):</strong> <strong>Disabled</strong> unless you specifically need this feature.</li>
  <li><strong>ErP Ready:</strong> <strong>Disabled</strong> usually allows USB power during S5/S4 states (for charging, etc.). Enable ErP for stricter power saving in off/hibernate states (often disables USB power). Set according to your preference; minimal performance impact.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>8. Saving, Testing, and Verification</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Save Changes:</strong> Once you have configured the settings, navigate to the <strong>Save &amp; Exit</strong> menu, select <strong>Save Changes and Reset</strong> (or similar wording), and confirm. The system will reboot with the new settings applied.</li>
  <li><strong>Stress Testing:</strong> This is crucial. After booting into the OS, run stability tests to ensure the system can handle sustained load with the new settings:
    <ul>
      <li><strong>CPU:</strong> Prime95 (Small FFTs test for maximum heat/power) or Cinebench R23 (multi-core test run for 10-30 minutes).</li>
      <li><strong>GPU:</strong> FurMark or Unigine Heaven/Superposition benchmark loops.</li>
      <li><strong>Combined:</strong> Run a demanding game or application, or a simultaneous CPU and GPU test (though less common).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Monitoring:</strong> While stress testing, use monitoring software like <strong>HWiNFO64</strong> (Sensors window) to watch:
    <ul>
      <li><strong>CPU Temperatures:</strong> Core temperatures should ideally stay below LEFTPAREN85-90^\circ CRIGHTPAREN under sustained load. Consistent temperatures above this indicate inadequate cooling or overly aggressive settings.</li>
      <li><strong>CPU Clock Speeds:</strong> Verify if the CPU reaches and sustains the expected boost clocks (up to 3.6 GHz for brief periods, potentially lower sustained clocks depending on PL1 and thermals).</li>
      <li><strong>Power Consumption:</strong> Observe Package Power to see if it respects the PL1/PL2 limits you set.</li>
      <li><strong>Throttling:</strong> Check for flags indicating Thermal Throttling, Power Limit Throttling (PL1/PL2), or Current/EDP Limit Throttling. If throttling occurs frequently, you may need to lower power limits, reduce voltage offset, or improve cooling.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Troubleshooting:</strong> If the system becomes unstable (crashes, fails to boot):
    <ul>
      <li>Re-enter the BIOS and revert the last change you made.</li>
      <li>If you cannot enter the BIOS, you may need to perform a <strong>CMOS reset</strong>. This usually involves unplugging the PC, removing the small coin-cell battery from the motherboard for a minute, or shorting specific “CMOS_CLR” jumper pins/pads on the motherboard as per the GMKtec G5 manual or documentation [User Context]. This will restore BIOS settings to factory defaults.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Remember, BIOS tuning is an iterative process. The optimal settings for your specific GMKtec G5 might require some experimentation based on your cooling, silicon lottery, and workload. Start with these recommendations and adjust based on careful testing and monitoring. Good luck!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Building and deploying a custom site using GitHub Actions and GitHub Pages</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/building-and-deploying-a-custom-site-using-github-actions-and-github-pages/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building and deploying a custom site using GitHub Actions and GitHub Pages" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T01:40:21+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/building-and-deploying-a-custom-site-using-github-actions-and-github-pages</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/building-and-deploying-a-custom-site-using-github-actions-and-github-pages/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>also check <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://github.com/simonw/git-scraper-template</code></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>I figured out a minimal pattern for building a completely custom website using GitHub Actions and deploying the result to GitHub Pages.</p>

<p>First you need to enable GitHub Pages for the repository. Navigate to Settings -&gt; Pages (or visit <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$repo/settings/pages</code>) and set the build source to “GitHub Actions”.</p>

<p>Here’s my minimal YAML recipe - save this in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.github/workflows/publish.yml</code> file:</p>

<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Publish site</span>

<span class="na">on</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">push</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">workflow_dispatch</span><span class="pi">:</span>

<span class="na">permissions</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">pages</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">write</span>
  <span class="na">id-token</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">write</span>

<span class="na">jobs</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">build</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="na">runs-on</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">ubuntu-latest</span>
    <span class="na">steps</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">uses</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">actions/checkout@v4</span>
    <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Build the site</span>
      <span class="na">run</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="pi">|</span>
        <span class="s">mkdir _site</span>
        <span class="s">echo '&lt;h1&gt;Hello, world!&lt;/h1&gt;' &gt; _site/index.html</span>
    <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Upload artifact</span>
      <span class="na">uses</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">actions/upload-pages-artifact@v3</span>
  <span class="na">deploy</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="na">environment</span><span class="pi">:</span>
      <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">github-pages</span>
      <span class="na">url</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">$</span>
    <span class="na">runs-on</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">ubuntu-latest</span>
    <span class="na">needs</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">build</span>
    <span class="na">steps</span><span class="pi">:</span>
      <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Deploy to GitHub Pages</span>
        <span class="na">id</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">deployment</span>
        <span class="na">uses</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">actions/deploy-pages@v4</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Anything that goes in that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_site/</code> directory will be published to the GitHub Pages site.</p>

<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">permissions</code> are required - the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pages: write</code> one enables writes to pages and for some reason the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">id-token: write</code> one is needed by the <a href="https://github.com/actions/deploy-pages">actions/deploy-pages</a> action.</p>

<p>The default URL for the site will be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://$GITHUB_USERNAME.github.io/$REPO_NAME/</code>. You can set this to <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site">custom domain</a> if you want.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/simonw/minimal-github-pages-from-actions/">github.com/simonw/minimal-github-pages-from-actions</a> is an example repository that uses this exact YAML configuration. It publishes a site to <a href="https://simonw.github.io/minimal-github-pages-from-actions/">https://simonw.github.io/minimal-github-pages-from-actions/</a>.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>

<p>You can combine this trick with scheduled workflows and <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2020/Oct/9/git-scraping/">Git scraping</a> to create all sorts of interesting and useful things.</p>

<p>I’m using it to publish <a href="https://simonw.github.io/recent-california-brown-pelicans/atom.xml">an Atom feed</a> of recent California Brown Pelicans sightings on <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/">iNaturalist</a> in my <a href="https://github.com/simonw/recent-california-brown-pelicans">simonw/recent-california-brown-pelicans</a> repository.</p>

<p>I also use it to publish my <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/">tools.simonwillison.net</a> site with a custom <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon">colophon</a> page - see <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/11/using-llms-for-code/#a-detailed-example">this post</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Clear Linux OS as a hypervisor to run the `sbnb.vhd` VM</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/clear-linux-os-as-a-hypervisor-to-run-the-sbnbvhd-vm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clear Linux OS as a hypervisor to run the `sbnb.vhd` VM" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/clear-linux-os-as-a-hypervisor-to-run-the-sbnbvhd-vm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/clear-linux-os-as-a-hypervisor-to-run-the-sbnbvhd-vm/"><![CDATA[<p>This guide presents two main methods:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Direct QEMU/KVM (Most Minimal):</strong> Using command-line tools directly for the lowest overhead.</li>
  <li><strong>Virt-Manager (User-Friendly Alternative):</strong> Using a graphical tool built on libvirt/QEMU for easier management.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Prerequisites (Apply to Both Methods)</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Clear Linux Host:</strong> A working Clear Linux installation.</li>
  <li><strong>Hardware Virtualization:</strong> Ensure Intel VT-x or AMD-V is enabled in your host machine’s BIOS/UEFI. Verify with:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>lscpu | <span class="nb">grep</span> <span class="nt">-E</span> <span class="s2">"svm|vmx"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Install Essential Bundles:</strong> Install KVM/QEMU, management libraries, and potentially tools for key handling.
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>swupd update
<span class="c"># Installs KVM/QEMU, libvirt, OVMF firmware, basic tools</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>swupd bundle-add kvm-host
<span class="c"># Optional: Install virt-manager GUI if using Method 2</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>swupd bundle-add virt-manager-gui
<span class="c"># Optional: Install mkisofs if using ISO for Tailscale key</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>swupd bundle-add cdrtools
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Enable Libvirt Daemon (Recommended, especially for Method 2):</strong>
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>systemctl <span class="nb">enable</span> <span class="nt">--now</span> libvirtd
<span class="c"># Verify it's running</span>
systemctl status libvirtd
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Obtain <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.vhd</code>:</strong> Download or copy the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.vhd</code> file onto your Clear Linux system.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Handling the SBNB Tailscale Key</strong></p>

<p>SBNB requires a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-tskey.txt</code> file containing your Tailscale authentication key to establish network connectivity during boot. It typically looks for this file in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/mnt/sbnb/</code> (from a USB drive) or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/mnt/vmware/</code> (VMware shared folder). Here are ways to provide it:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Method A: ISO Image (Recommended for Simplicity)</strong>
    <ol>
      <li>Create the key file: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">echo "YOUR_TAILSCALE_KEY" &gt; sbnb-tskey.txt</code></li>
      <li>Create an ISO (requires <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cdrtools</code> bundle): <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mkisofs -o sbnb-key.iso sbnb-tskey.txt</code></li>
      <li>Attach this <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-key.iso</code> as a CD-ROM drive to the VM. SBNB’s boot script should find and mount the CD-ROM to read the key.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Method B: Virtual FAT32 USB Drive (More Complex Setup)</strong>
    <ol>
      <li>Create an image file: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dd if=/dev/zero of=sbnb-key.img bs=1M count=10</code></li>
      <li>Format it: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mkfs.vfat sbnb-key.img</code></li>
      <li>Mount, copy <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-tskey.txt</code> (ensure exact filename), unmount (see previous response for detailed steps).</li>
      <li>Attach this <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-key.img</code> as a USB storage device.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Method 1: Direct QEMU/KVM (Most Minimal)</strong></p>

<p>This method avoids graphical tools and management layers like libvirt.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Verify OVMF Path:</strong> The UEFI firmware is essential. Find its path. Common locations:
    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/usr/share/qemu/OVMF.fd</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/usr/share/ovmf/OVMF.fd</code>
Check with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls /usr/share/qemu/*.fd</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls /usr/share/ovmf/*.fd</code>. Ensure the file exists.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Launch Command:</strong>
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>qemu-system-x86_64 <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-enable-kvm</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-m</span> 1G <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-smp</span> 2 <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-cpu</span> host <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-bios</span> /usr/share/qemu/OVMF.fd <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-drive</span> <span class="nv">file</span><span class="o">=</span>sbnb.vhd,format<span class="o">=</span>vpc,if<span class="o">=</span>virtio <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-cdrom</span> sbnb-key.iso <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-netdev</span> user,id<span class="o">=</span>net0 <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-device</span> virtio-net-pci,netdev<span class="o">=</span>net0 <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-nographic</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-enable-kvm</code>: Use hardware virtualization.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-m 1G</code>: 1GB RAM (adjust as needed).</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-smp 2</code>: 2 vCPUs (adjust as needed).</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-cpu host</code>: Pass through host CPU features (good for performance).</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-bios /path/to/OVMF.fd</code>: <strong>CRITICAL:</strong> Use the verified path to UEFI firmware.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-drive file=sbnb.vhd,format=vpc,if=virtio</code>: Use the VHD directly (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">format=vpc</code>) with the high-performance <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virtio</code> block driver.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-cdrom sbnb-key.iso</code>: Attach the Tailscale key ISO (using Method A above). (Alternatively, use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-usb -device usb-storage...</code> for Method B).</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-netdev user,id=net0 -device virtio-net-pci,netdev=net0</code>: Basic user-mode networking using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virtio</code>.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-nographic</code>: Run headless. Remove for a graphical console window.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Method 2: Virt-Manager (User-Friendly Alternative)</strong></p>

<p>This uses the graphical <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virt-manager</code> tool.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Launch Virt-Manager:</strong> Open the application (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virt-manager</code>).</li>
  <li><strong>Create New VM:</strong> Click “File” -&gt; “New Virtual Machine”.</li>
  <li><strong>Choose Import:</strong> Select “Import existing disk image”.</li>
  <li><strong>Provide Disk Path:</strong> Browse to and select your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.vhd</code> file. QEMU/KVM (via libvirt) can often handle VHD directly.</li>
  <li><strong>OS Type:</strong> Choose “Linux” -&gt; “Generic” or a specific version if known (e.g., “Generic Linux 2020”).</li>
  <li><strong>Memory/CPU:</strong> Allocate RAM (e.g., 1024 MiB) and CPUs (e.g., 2).</li>
  <li><strong>Customize Before Install:</strong> <strong>Check the box</strong> “Customize configuration before install”. Click “Finish”.</li>
  <li><strong>Configuration:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Overview/Firmware:</strong> <strong>CRITICAL:</strong> Ensure “Firmware” is set to <strong>UEFI</strong> (it might show a path like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/usr/share/qemu/OVMF.fd</code>).</li>
      <li><strong>Disk:</strong> Select the imported disk (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.vhd</code>). Under “Advanced options”, ensure “Disk bus” is set to <strong>VirtIO</strong> for best performance. (Use SATA only if VirtIO causes issues).</li>
      <li><strong>Add Hardware (Tailscale Key):</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>Click “Add Hardware”.</li>
          <li>Select “Storage”.</li>
          <li>Choose “Select or create custom storage”.</li>
          <li>Device type: “CDROM device”.</li>
          <li>Click “Manage…”, browse to and select your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-key.iso</code> (created using Method A above).</li>
          <li>Click “Finish”.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><strong>NIC:</strong> Ensure the network interface device model is <strong>virtio</strong>.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Begin Installation:</strong> Click “Begin Installation”. The VM will boot using the VHD and the attached ISO for the key.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Optional: VHD to QCOW2 Conversion</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Why?</strong> While QEMU/KVM can use VHD (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">vpc</code>) directly, converting to QCOW2 (QEMU’s native format) can offer better performance and features like snapshots.</li>
  <li><strong>How?</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qemu-img convert -p -f vpc -O qcow2 sbnb.vhd sbnb.qcow2</code></li>
  <li><strong>Usage:</strong> If converted, simply point your QEMU command (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-drive file=sbnb.qcow2,format=qcow2,...</code>) or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virt-manager</code> import step to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.qcow2</code> file instead of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.vhd</code> file. This conversion is <strong>not strictly required</strong> but often recommended.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Verification</strong></p>

<p>After starting the VM using either method:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Monitor your Tailscale Admin Console. The new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-</code> device should appear.</li>
  <li>SSH into the device using its Tailscale IP or MagicDNS name.</li>
  <li>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb-dev-env.sh</code> if needed for development tasks.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">how to manage multiple Docker containers</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/how-to-manage-multiple-docker-containers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to manage multiple Docker containers" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T23:36:27+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/how-to-manage-multiple-docker-containers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/how-to-manage-multiple-docker-containers/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>1. Finding Your “Lost” Docker Containers</strong></p>

<p>When you say you’ve “lost” containers, it usually means you don’t know if they are running, what their names or IDs are, or how to connect to them. The first step is to list <em>all</em> containers Docker knows about, including stopped ones:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker ps <span class="nt">-a</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps</code>: By itself, this command shows only <em>currently running</em> containers.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-a</code> (or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--all</code>): This flag is crucial; it shows <em>all</em> containers, running or stopped.</li>
</ul>

<p>The output will give you columns like:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CONTAINER ID</code>: A unique identifier. You can use the first few characters.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">IMAGE</code>: The image the container was created from (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nginx</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mysql</code>).</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">COMMAND</code>: The command the container is running or ran.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CREATED</code>: When the container was created.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">STATUS</code>: Shows if it’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Up</code> (running) or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Exited</code> (stopped), along with how long.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PORTS</code>: Any port mappings.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NAMES</code>: Docker assigns a random two-word name if you don’t provide one (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jolly_wozniak</code>).</li>
</ul>

<p>Look through this list to identify the containers you started. Note their <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CONTAINER ID</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NAMES</code>.</p>

<p><strong>2. Running Containers Persistently (and Not Losing Them!)</strong></p>

<p>To avoid losing track and ensure containers keep running after you start them, follow these practices:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Run in Detached Mode (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-d</code>):</strong> This runs the container in the background, so it doesn’t stop when you close your terminal.</li>
  <li><strong>Assign a Name (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--name</code>):</strong> Give your containers memorable names. This makes them much easier to manage than using random names or long IDs.</li>
</ul>

<p>Example: Starting an Nginx web server container:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># docker run [options] &lt;image_name&gt; [command]</span>
docker run <span class="nt">-d</span> <span class="nt">--name</span> my-webserver nginx
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-d</code>: Detach (run in background).</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--name my-webserver</code>: Assigns the name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">my-webserver</code>.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nginx</code>: The image to use.</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, if you run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps</code>, you should see <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">my-webserver</code> listed as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Up</code>.</p>

<p><strong>3. Interacting with Running Containers (“Switching”)</strong></p>

<p>“Switching” between containers means changing which container you are interacting with. Since containers run concurrently in the background (when started with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-d</code>), you use commands to execute commands <em>inside</em> a specific container or attach to its main process.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker exec</code> (Recommended for Interaction):</strong> This command executes a <em>new</em> command inside an <em>already running</em> container. It’s the safest and most common way to get a shell or run utilities inside a container without disturbing its main process.</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># docker exec [options] &lt;container_name_or_id&gt; &lt;command&gt;</span>
docker <span class="nb">exec</span> <span class="nt">-it</span> my-webserver /bin/bash
</code></pre></div>    </div>

    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-i</code> (interactive): Keeps STDIN open even if not attached.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-t</code> (tty): Allocates a pseudo-TTY (makes it look like a normal terminal session).</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">my-webserver</code>: The name of the container you want to enter.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/bin/bash</code>: The command to run inside the container (you might need <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/bin/sh</code> if bash isn’t installed in the minimal image).</li>
    </ul>

    <p>You are now “inside” the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">my-webserver</code> container. You can run commands there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Detaching Safely:</strong> To leave the container’s shell (from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker exec -it</code>) without stopping it, press the key sequence: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ctrl + P</code>, then <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ctrl + Q</code>. You’ll return to your host system’s prompt, and the container keeps running.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker attach</code> (Use with Caution):</strong> This command attaches your terminal’s standard input, output, and error streams directly to the <em>main process</em> running inside the container (the one started by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker run</code>).</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Risk:</strong> If you exit this attached shell (e.g., using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">exit</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ctrl+D</code>), and that causes the container’s main process to terminate, the container <em>will stop</em>.</li>
      <li>Generally, prefer <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker exec</code> for interactive shells. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">attach</code> is more for seeing the direct output of the main process.</li>
    </ul>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># docker attach &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;</span>
docker attach my-webserver
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>(Again, use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ctrl+P, Ctrl+Q</code> to detach without stopping).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Viewing Container Logs</strong></p>

<p>To see the output (logs) from a container’s main process, especially for detached containers:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># See all logs</span>
docker logs &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;

<span class="c"># Follow logs in real-time (like tail -f)</span>
docker logs <span class="nt">-f</span> &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Example: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker logs -f my-webserver</code></p>

<p><strong>5. Managing Container Lifecycle (Stopping and Removing)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Stopping a Container:</strong>
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker stop &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>This sends a SIGTERM signal, then a SIGKILL after a grace period.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Starting a Stopped Container:</strong>
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker start &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Removing a Stopped Container:</strong> You can only remove stopped containers unless you force it.
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker <span class="nb">rm</span> &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Removing a Running Container (Force):</strong> Use with caution, data may be lost.
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker <span class="nb">rm</span> <span class="nt">-f</span> &lt;container_name_or_id&gt;
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Cleaning Up:</strong> To remove all stopped containers:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker container prune
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>(It will ask for confirmation).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>6. Broader Context: KVM/QEMU and Buildroot</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>KVM/QEMU:</strong> Managing KVM/QEMU virtual machines is separate from Docker. You’ll use different tools, typically <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libvirt</code> (with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virsh</code> command-line tool) or direct <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qemu-system-*</code> commands. Docker containers share the host kernel; KVM VMs run full separate OS instances with virtualized hardware. They can run concurrently with Docker containers if your system has enough resources (CPU, RAM).</li>
  <li><strong>Buildroot System:</strong> Since you’re on a custom Buildroot system, be mindful of resource constraints. It’s likely a minimal environment. Running many Docker containers <em>and</em> KVM virtual machines simultaneously might strain CPU, RAM, and disk I/O. Ensure Docker Engine and KVM/QEMU packages were correctly included and configured in your Buildroot build.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Summary of Key Docker Commands for Your Goal:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Find all containers: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps -a</code></li>
  <li>Start container in background with a name: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker run -d --name &lt;your_name&gt; &lt;image&gt;</code></li>
  <li>See running containers: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps</code></li>
  <li>Interact with a running container: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker exec -it &lt;name_or_id&gt; /bin/sh</code> (or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/bin/bash</code>)</li>
  <li>Detach from interaction: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ctrl+P, Ctrl+Q</code></li>
  <li>View logs: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker logs &lt;name_or_id&gt;</code> (add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-f</code> to follow)</li>
  <li>Stop container: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker stop &lt;name_or_id&gt;</code></li>
  <li>Remove stopped container: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker rm &lt;name_or_id&gt;</code></li>
</ul>

<p>By using detached mode (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-d</code>) and naming (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--name</code>) consistently, and utilizing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps -a</code> to find things, you should be able to manage and “switch” between your Docker containers effectively. Remember that KVM management is a separate task using different tools.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">sbnb buildroot intel n97 fix</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/sbnb-buildroot-intel-n97-fix/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sbnb buildroot intel n97 fix" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T22:13:51+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/sbnb-buildroot-intel-n97-fix</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/sbnb-buildroot-intel-n97-fix/"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, let’s refactor the provided Buildroot files (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code>) to permanently include the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> kernel parameter for the boot process initiated by the custom EFI executable.</p>

<p>The main challenge here is that your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> script <strong>builds a unified EFI executable and hardcodes the kernel command line within itself</strong>. This approach bypasses the standard Buildroot mechanism for setting the kernel command line via <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</code> options in the configuration, which are typically used by bootloaders like GRUB or Syslinux.</p>

<p>Therefore, to add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code>, we must modify the script directly. Changes to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code> file will primarily involve ensuring other settings (like the initramfs format) are consistent with the script and adding comments for clarity.</p>

<p><strong>1. Refactored <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh</code></strong></p>

<p>This version adds <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> to the command line string and includes a note about a potentially unused variable from the original script.</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">#!/bin/bash</span>

<span class="nb">set</span> <span class="nt">-euxo</span> pipefail

<span class="c"># This script creates a custom bootable EFI binary by combining an EFI stub,</span>
<span class="c"># Linux kernel, initrd, osrel and cmdline.</span>

<span class="c"># Define variables</span>
<span class="nv">STUB</span><span class="o">=</span>/usr/lib/systemd/boot/efi/linuxx64.efi.stub
<span class="nv">KERNEL</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">BINARIES_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">/bzImage"</span>
<span class="c"># --- VERIFY THIS INITRD PATH ---</span>
<span class="c"># Ensure this path correctly points to the CPIO archive you intend to use.</span>
<span class="c"># Buildroot generates the CPIO in ${BINARIES_DIR}. Check if it's compressed</span>
<span class="c"># (e.g., rootfs-sbnb.cpio.xz) or uncompressed (e.g., rootfs-sbnb.cpio)</span>
<span class="c"># and adjust this variable and/or your Buildroot config accordingly.</span>
<span class="c"># See notes in the defconfig section below.</span>
<span class="nv">INITRD</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">BINARIES_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">/rootfs-sbnb.cpio"</span>
<span class="nv">OS_RELEASE</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">TARGET_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">/etc/os-release"</span>
<span class="c"># --- MODIFIED KERNEL COMMAND LINE ---</span>
<span class="c"># Added 'nomodeset' to the end of the command line string.</span>
<span class="c"># IMPORTANT: This command line is HARDCODED. Changes to BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</span>
<span class="c"># in the Buildroot config will NOT affect the EFI file generated by this script.</span>
<span class="nv">CMDLINE</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"console=tty0 console=ttyS0 earlyprintk verbose intel_iommu=on module_blacklist=nouveau,nvidiafb,snd_hda_intel dyndbg=</span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s2">module firmware_class +p; module microcode +p; module ccp +p</span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s2"> nomodeset"</span>
<span class="c"># --- END MODIFICATION ---</span>
<span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">mktemp</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="nv">OUTPUT</span><span class="o">=</span>sbnb.efi <span class="c"># Output filename in the current directory</span>

<span class="c"># Write the command line to a temporary file</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="nt">-n</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>

<span class="c"># Calculate alignment</span>
<span class="nv">align</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">$(</span>objdump <span class="nt">-p</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">STUB</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> | <span class="nb">awk</span> <span class="s1">'{ if ($1 == "SectionAlignment"){print $2} }'</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="nv">align</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span><span class="m">16</span><span class="c">#$align))</span>

<span class="c"># Calculate offsets for sections</span>
<span class="nv">stub_line</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span>objdump <span class="nt">-h</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">STUB</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> | <span class="nb">tail</span> <span class="nt">-2</span> | <span class="nb">head</span> <span class="nt">-1</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="nv">stub_size</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="m">0</span>x<span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$stub_line</span><span class="s2">"</span> | <span class="nb">awk</span> <span class="s1">'{print $3}'</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="nv">stub_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="m">0</span>x<span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$stub_line</span><span class="s2">"</span> | <span class="nb">awk</span> <span class="s1">'{print $4}'</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="nv">osrel_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>stub_size <span class="o">+</span> stub_offs<span class="k">))</span>
<span class="nv">osrel_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>osrel_offs <span class="o">+</span> align <span class="o">-</span> osrel_offs <span class="o">%</span> align<span class="k">))</span>
<span class="nv">cmdline_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>osrel_offs <span class="o">+</span> <span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">stat</span> <span class="nt">-Lc</span>%s <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OS_RELEASE</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="k">))</span>
<span class="nv">cmdline_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>cmdline_offs <span class="o">+</span> align <span class="o">-</span> cmdline_offs <span class="o">%</span> align<span class="k">))</span>
<span class="c"># --- NOTE: splash_offs Calculation ---</span>
<span class="c"># The following offset is calculated but doesn't appear to be used in the</span>
<span class="c"># objcopy command below in the original script. Verify if this is intended.</span>
<span class="nv">splash_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>cmdline_offs <span class="o">+</span> <span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">stat</span> <span class="nt">-Lc</span>%s <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="k">))</span>
<span class="nv">splash_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>splash_offs <span class="o">+</span> align <span class="o">-</span> splash_offs <span class="o">%</span> align<span class="k">))</span>
<span class="c"># --- END NOTE ---</span>
<span class="nv">linux_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>splash_offs<span class="k">))</span> <span class="c"># Original script sets linux_offs based on splash_offs</span>
<span class="nv">initrd_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>linux_offs <span class="o">+</span> <span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">stat</span> <span class="nt">-Lc</span>%s <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">KERNEL</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">)</span><span class="k">))</span>
<span class="nv">initrd_offs</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>initrd_offs <span class="o">+</span> align <span class="o">-</span> initrd_offs <span class="o">%</span> align<span class="k">))</span>

<span class="c"># Use objcopy to add sections to the EFI stub</span>
<span class="c"># Ensure all required files exist before running objcopy</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OS_RELEASE</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">KERNEL</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INITRD</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then
    </span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"Error: One or more input files for objcopy not found!"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="m">2</span>
    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"OS_RELEASE: </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OS_RELEASE</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="m">2</span>
    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"CMDLINE_TMP: </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="m">2</span>
    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"KERNEL: </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">KERNEL</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="m">2</span>
    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"INITRD: </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INITRD</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">&gt;&amp;</span><span class="m">2</span>
    <span class="nb">rm</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="c"># Clean up temp file on error</span>
    <span class="nb">exit </span><span class="m">1</span>
<span class="k">fi

</span>objcopy <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="o">--</span>add-section .osrel<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OS_RELEASE</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">--</span>change-section-vma .osrel<span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">printf </span>0x%x <span class="nv">$osrel_offs</span><span class="si">)</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="o">--</span>add-section .cmdline<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">--</span>change-section-vma .cmdline<span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">printf </span>0x%x <span class="nv">$cmdline_offs</span><span class="si">)</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="o">--</span>add-section .linux<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">KERNEL</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">--</span>change-section-vma .linux<span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">printf </span>0x%x <span class="nv">$linux_offs</span><span class="si">)</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="o">--</span>add-section .initrd<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INITRD</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">--</span>change-section-vma .initrd<span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">printf </span>0x%x <span class="nv">$initrd_offs</span><span class="si">)</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">STUB</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OUTPUT</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>

<span class="c"># Clean up temporary file</span>
<span class="nb">rm</span> <span class="o">-</span>f <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CMDLINE_TMP</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>

<span class="c"># Output the result</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"Unified EFI executable created: </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OUTPUT</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>

<span class="c"># Move the final EFI file to the standard Buildroot images directory</span>
<span class="c"># BR2_ROOTFS_POST_IMAGE_SCRIPT runs from the Buildroot top-level directory.</span>
<span class="c"># ${BINARIES_DIR} correctly points to output/images in this context.</span>
<span class="nb">mv</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OUTPUT</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">BINARIES_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">/"</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"Moved </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">OUTPUT</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2"> to </span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">BINARIES_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">/"</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>2. Refactored <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">configs/sbnb_defconfig</code></strong></p>

<p>This version includes comments explaining the implications of the custom script and provides guidance on CPIO and Syslinux settings.</p>

<div class="language-makefile highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nv">BR2_x86_64</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_CCACHE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_INIT_SYSTEMD</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_SYSTEM_DEFAULT_PATH</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_GENERATE_LOCALE</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"en_US"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_ROOTFS_OVERLAY</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/rootfs-overlay"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_ROOTFS_PRE_BUILD_SCRIPT</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/pre_build.sh"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_ROOTFS_POST_BUILD_SCRIPT</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/post_build.sh"</span>

<span class="c"># --- Custom EFI Generation ---
# This post-image script creates a unified EFI executable (sbnb.efi)
# IMPORTANT: The kernel command line is HARDCODED inside the create_efi.sh script.
# Standard BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_* options below will NOT affect sbnb.efi.
</span><span class="nv">BR2_ROOTFS_POST_IMAGE_SCRIPT</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh"</span>

<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_GZIP</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_USE_CUSTOM_CONFIG</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># Switch back to upstream kernel once Restricted Injection hypervisor support
# patches merged: https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/Z08J0EVu0VeA7Z%2FR@rli9-mobl/T/
</span><span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_GIT</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_REPO_URL</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"https://github.com/coconut-svsm/linux.git"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_REPO_VERSION</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"svsm"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_CONFIG_FILE</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/kernel-config"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"kernel-config-firmware"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_NEEDS_HOST_LIBELF</span><span class="o">=</span>y

<span class="c"># --- Kernel Command Line (Standard Bootloaders Only) ---
# These settings configure bootloaders like Syslinux or GRUB.
# They are NOT used by the custom create_efi.sh script.
# If Syslinux (enabled below) is actually used as a boot method,
# you SHOULD configure these options appropriately for it.
# Otherwise, the Syslinux boot entry might use an empty or default command line.
# Example:
# BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_EXTEND=y
# BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_FRAGMENT="nomodeset console=tty1"
</span><span class="nv">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_DEFAULT</span><span class="o">=</span>y <span class="c"># Or choose custom/extend as needed for Syslinux</span>
<span class="c"># BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_CUSTOM is not set
# BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_EXTEND is not set
# BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_FRAGMENT=""
</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_LINUX_HEADERS_CUSTOM_6_11</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># ... (other packages remain the same) ...
</span><span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_LINUX_TOOLS_CPUPOWER</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_XZ</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_STRACE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS_DEBUGFS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS_E2IMAGE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS_E4DEFRAG</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS_FUSE2FS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_E2FSPROGS_RESIZE2FS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_XORG7</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_XLIB_LIBX11</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DMIDECODE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HWDATA</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HWDATA_IAB_OUI_TXT</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HWDATA_PNP_IDS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># BR2_PACKAGE_HWDATA_USB_IDS is not set
</span><span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_INTEL_MICROCODE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_IPMITOOL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_IPMITOOL_LANPLUS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_NVME</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_PARTED</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_SYSSTAT</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_CA_CERTIFICATES</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_LIBOPENSSL_BIN</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_LIBCURL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_LIBCURL_CURL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_SLANG</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_BIRD</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_NETCAT_OPENBSD</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_OPENSSH</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_WIREGUARD_TOOLS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_SUDO</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_TMUX</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_CLI_BUILDX</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_COMPOSE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_ENGINE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_ENGINE_DRIVER_BTRFS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_ENGINE_DRIVER_DEVICEMAPPER</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOCKER_ENGINE_DRIVER_VFS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_EFIBOOTMGR</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_UTIL_LINUX_WIPEFS</span><span class="o">=</span>y

<span class="c"># --- Syslinux Bootloader ---
# Syslinux is enabled here for MBR and EFI.
# If you ONLY boot using the custom sbnb.efi generated by the script,
# you might consider disabling Syslinux to avoid confusion:
# # BR2_TARGET_SYSLINUX is not set
# If Syslinux IS used (e.g., for USB boot), ensure the standard kernel
# command line options above (BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*) are set correctly for it.
</span><span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_SYSLINUX</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_SYSLINUX_MBR</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_SYSLINUX_EFI</span><span class="o">=</span>y

<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_KMOD_XZ</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># ... (other host packages) ...
</span><span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_BZIP2</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_XZ</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_CURSES</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_SSL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_TAILSCALE</span><span class="o">=</span>y

<span class="c"># --- Root Filesystem / Initramfs Generation ---
</span><span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># IMPORTANT: Verify CPIO format needed by create_efi.sh!
# The script uses INITRD="${BINARIES_DIR}/rootfs-sbnb.cpio".
# This implies an UNCOMPRESSED CPIO archive.
# Your original defconfig had BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ=y, which creates
# a compressed file (e.g., rootfs.cpio.xz or rootfs-sbnb.cpio.xz).
#
# ACTION REQUIRED:
# 1. Determine if create_efi.sh truly needs an UNCOMPRESSED CPIO.
# 2. If YES: Use BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE=y below.
# 3. If NO (it needs a compressed CPIO like XZ):
#    a. Change the INITRD variable in create_efi.sh to the correct compressed filename
#       (e.g., INITRD="${BINARIES_DIR}/rootfs-sbnb.cpio.xz").
#    b. Use the corresponding compression option below (e.g., BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ=y).
#
# Assuming UNCOMPRESSED based on script variable:
</span><span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="c"># BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_GZIP is not set
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_BZIP2 is not set
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_LZMA is not set
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_LZO is not set
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_LZ4 is not set
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ is not set # Make sure this is commented out if using NONE
# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_ZSTD is not set
# Set the output filename to match the script variable:
</span><span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_FILENAME</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"rootfs-sbnb.cpio"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_OPTS</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">""</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_ARGS</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">""</span>

<span class="c"># ... (rest of packages remain the same) ...
</span><span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_SEVCTL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_SNPGUEST</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_TPM2_TOOLS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_BUSYBOX_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">$(</span><span class="s2">BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="s2">/board/sbnb/sbnb/busybox.fragment"</span>
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS4_XZ</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_OPENVMTOOLS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_SHARED_STATIC_LIBS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_FATRESIZE</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_MOKUTIL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_TCPDUMP</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOSFSTOOLS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOSFSTOOLS_FATLABEL</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOSFSTOOLS_FSCK_FAT</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_DOSFSTOOLS_MKFS_FAT</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON3</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON_PIP</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON3_ZLIB</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON_REQUESTS</span><span class="o">=</span>y
<span class="nv">BR2_PACKAGE_JQ</span><span class="o">=</span>y

</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>3. Explanation of Changes and Important Considerations:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code>:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> was added to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CMDLINE</code> variable.</li>
      <li>A check was added to ensure input files exist before <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">objcopy</code> runs.</li>
      <li>A comment was added regarding the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD</code> variable path – <strong>you must verify</strong> if your script needs a compressed (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.xz</code>) or uncompressed CPIO file and adjust the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD</code> variable in the script and the CPIO settings in the defconfig accordingly.</li>
      <li>A note was added about the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">splash_offs</code> variable, which seems calculated but unused in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">objcopy</code> command of the original script. You may want to investigate this.</li>
      <li>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rm</code> command ensures the temporary command line file is deleted.</li>
      <li>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mv</code> command ensures the final <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.efi</code> is placed in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output/images/</code>.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code>:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>CPIO Configuration:</strong> This is the most critical part to verify. The configuration is set up assuming the script needs an <em>uncompressed</em> CPIO named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rootfs-sbnb.cpio</code>, based on the script’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD</code> variable. If your original <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ=y</code> setting was intentional and the script <em>should</em> use a compressed initrd, you need to:
        <ol>
          <li>Change <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD</code> in the script (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD="${BINARIES_DIR}/rootfs-sbnb.cpio.xz"</code>).</li>
          <li>Change the defconfig back to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ=y</code> (and comment out <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE=y</code>).</li>
          <li>Ensure <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_FILENAME</code> results in the correct name if needed (it might default correctly if compression is enabled).</li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      <li><strong>Kernel Command Line:</strong> Comments explicitly state that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</code> options are ignored by the script but <em>are</em> relevant for Syslinux. You need to decide:
        <ul>
          <li>If Syslinux is used: Configure <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</code> appropriately for it.</li>
          <li>If Syslinux is NOT used: Consider disabling <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_SYSLINUX*</code> options to avoid confusion.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><strong>Comments:</strong> Added comments to explain the hardcoded command line, the CPIO verification need, and the Syslinux interaction.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Next Steps:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Verify CPIO Requirement:</strong> Determine the exact initramfs file (compressed or uncompressed, exact name) that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> is intended to embed.</li>
  <li><strong>Apply Changes:</strong> Replace your existing files with these refactored versions, making sure the CPIO settings in <em>both</em> the script (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INITRD</code> variable) and the defconfig (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_*</code>) are consistent with your verified requirement. Adjust Syslinux settings as needed.</li>
  <li><strong>Rebuild:</strong> Navigate to your Buildroot top-level directory and run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">make</code>. This will rebuild the necessary components and execute the post-image script.</li>
  <li><strong>Deploy:</strong> Use the updated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output/images/sbnb.efi</code> file to boot your GMKtec G5.</li>
  <li><strong>Verify:</strong> After booting, log in and run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cat /proc/cmdline</code> to confirm that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> is present in the kernel command line arguments.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>5. Further Considerations / Alternatives:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Reading Command Line from Buildroot:</strong> Instead of hardcoding the command line in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code>, a more robust approach would be to modify the script to read the command line configured via Buildroot’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</code> options. This could involve reading the generated bootloader config file (like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">syslinux.cfg</code>) or having Buildroot write the command line to a temporary file that the script reads. This makes configuration more centralized but requires more significant script changes.</li>
  <li><strong>Script Robustness:</strong> The provided <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> could benefit from more robust error checking (e.g., verifying <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">objcopy</code> success).</li>
</ul>

<p>By applying these changes and carefully verifying the CPIO configuration, you should successfully embed the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> parameter into your custom EFI boot process.</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="second-approach">second approach</h1>

<p>Okay, let’s refine the approach for adding the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> kernel parameter to your Buildroot OS image, specifically addressing the interaction between your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code> and the custom <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> script.</p>

<p><strong>Understanding the Context</strong></p>

<p>Your setup uses a custom post-image script (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh</code>) to generate a unified EFI executable (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.efi</code>). The critical point is that, in its original form, this script <strong>hardcodes the kernel command line arguments</strong> within the script itself. This bypasses Buildroot’s standard mechanism for managing kernel parameters via the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> variable (or older <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_*</code> options) in the configuration (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">defconfig</code>).</p>

<p>Therefore, simply setting <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code> will <em>not</em> affect the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.efi</code> file generated by the original script.</p>

<p>We need to modify the system so that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> is included in the command line embedded within <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb.efi</code>. There are two main ways to achieve this:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Solution A (Quick Fix):</strong> Modify the script to include <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> in its hardcoded command line string. This is simpler but less maintainable.</li>
  <li><strong>Solution B (Recommended):</strong> Modify the script to <em>read</em> the command line from the Buildroot environment variable <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> and define <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sbnb_defconfig</code>. This aligns with standard Buildroot practices and centralizes configuration.</li>
</ol>

<p>We will also ensure the Buildroot configuration correctly generates the CPIO root filesystem expected by the script.</p>

<p><strong>Rationale Recap:</strong> The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> parameter is being added as a troubleshooting step. It tells the kernel <em>not</em> to load video drivers and attempt display mode changes during initialization. This can prevent hangs or slowdowns caused by graphics driver issues on certain hardware, like the slow console output you observed.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Solution A: Modify Hardcoded Command Line in Script (Quick Fix)</strong></p>

<p>This approach directly edits the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CMDLINE</code> variable within <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code>.</p>

<p><strong>1. Modify <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh</code>:</strong></p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">--- a/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh
</span><span class="p">@@ -10,8 +10,10 @@</span>
 KERNEL="${BINARIES_DIR}/bzImage"
 INITRD="${BINARIES_DIR}/rootfs-sbnb.cpio"
 OS_RELEASE="${TARGET_DIR}/etc/os-release"
<span class="gd">-CMDLINE="console=tty0 console=ttyS0 earlyprintk verbose intel_iommu=on module_blacklist=nouveau,nvidiafb,snd_hda_intel dyndbg=\"module firmware_class +p; module microcode +p; module ccp +p\""
</span><span class="gi">+# --- MODIFIED KERNEL COMMAND LINE (Hardcoded) ---
+# Added 'nomodeset'. Note: This bypasses standard Buildroot BR2_CMDLINE config.
+CMDLINE="console=tty0 console=ttyS0 earlyprintk verbose intel_iommu=on module_blacklist=nouveau,nvidiafb,snd_hda_intel dyndbg=\"module firmware_class +p; module microcode +p; module ccp +p\" nomodeset"
+# --- END MODIFICATION ---
</span> CMDLINE_TMP=$(mktemp)
 OUTPUT=sbnb.efi
<span class="err">
</span><span class="p">@@ -41,8 +43,13 @@</span>
     --add-section .initrd="${INITRD}" --change-section-vma .initrd=$(printf 0x%x $initrd_offs) \
     "${STUB}" "${OUTPUT}"
<span class="err">
</span><span class="gi">+# Clean up temporary file
+rm -f "${CMDLINE_TMP}"
+
</span> # Output the result
 echo "Output: ${OUTPUT}"
<span class="gi">+
+# Move the final EFI file to the standard Buildroot images directory (BINARIES_DIR=output/images)
+mv "${OUTPUT}" "${BINARIES_DIR}/"
+echo "Moved ${OUTPUT} to ${BINARIES_DIR}/"
</span><span class="err">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Change:</strong> Added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> to the end of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CMDLINE</code> variable string.</li>
  <li><strong>Added:</strong> Cleanup for the temporary file (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rm -f "${CMDLINE_TMP}"</code>).</li>
  <li><strong>Added:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mv "${OUTPUT}" "${BINARIES_DIR}/"</code> to place the final artifact in the correct Buildroot output directory (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output/images</code>). Buildroot provides <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BINARIES_DIR</code> in the environment when running post-image scripts.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Modify <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">configs/sbnb_defconfig</code> (CPIO Settings &amp; Comments):</strong></p>

<p>Ensure the CPIO settings match what the script expects (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rootfs-sbnb.cpio</code>, likely uncompressed). Add comments clarifying the hardcoded nature.</p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">--- a/configs/sbnb_defconfig
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/configs/sbnb_defconfig
</span><span class="p">@@ -8,9 +8,10 @@</span>
 BR2_ROOTFS_OVERLAY="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/rootfs-overlay"
 BR2_ROOTFS_PRE_BUILD_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/pre_build.sh"
 BR2_ROOTFS_POST_BUILD_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/post_build.sh"
<span class="gi">+# This post-image script creates a unified EFI executable (sbnb.efi)
+# IMPORTANT: With Solution A, the kernel command line is HARDCODED inside create_efi.sh
+# Standard BR2_CMDLINE options will NOT affect sbnb.efi in this case.
</span> BR2_ROOTFS_POST_IMAGE_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh"
<span class="gd">-BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_GZIP=y
</span> BR2_LINUX_KERNEL=y
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_USE_CUSTOM_CONFIG=y
 # Switch back to upstream kernel once Restricted Injection hypervisor support
<span class="p">@@ -20,6 +21,7 @@</span>
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_REPO_VERSION="svsm"
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_CONFIG_FILE="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/kernel-config"
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="kernel-config-firmware"
<span class="gi">+# BR2_CMDLINE is not set here as it's bypassed by the script in Solution A
</span> BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_NEEDS_HOST_LIBELF=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_LINUX_HEADERS_CUSTOM_6_11=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_LINUX_TOOLS_CPUPOWER=y
<span class="p">@@ -75,14 +77,11 @@</span>
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_CURSES=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_SSL=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_TAILSCALE=y
<span class="gi">+# Configure CPIO rootfs generation to match the script's expectation
</span> BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO=y
<span class="gd">-# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ is not set
-BR2_PACKAGE_SEVCTL=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_SNPGUEST=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_TPM2_TOOLS=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_BUSYBOX_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/busybox.fragment"
-BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS=y
-BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS4_XZ=y
</span><span class="gi">+# Ensure CPIO is not compressed as the script uses the base name 'rootfs-sbnb.cpio'
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE=y
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_FILENAME="rootfs-sbnb.cpio"
</span> BR2_PACKAGE_OPENVMTOOLS=y
 BR2_SHARED_STATIC_LIBS=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_FATRESIZE=y
<span class="p">@@ -97,4 +96,10 @@</span>
 BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON3_ZLIB=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON_REQUESTS=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_JQ=y
<span class="gi">+BR2_PACKAGE_SEVCTL=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_SNPGUEST=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_TPM2_TOOLS=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_BUSYBOX_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/busybox.fragment"
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS=y
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS4_XZ=y
</span><span class="err">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Changes:</strong> Added comments about the hardcoded command line. Explicitly set <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE=y</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_FILENAME="rootfs-sbnb.cpio"</code> to ensure the correct, uncompressed CPIO file is generated for the script. Removed <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_GZIP=y</code> as the script uses <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bzImage</code>, implying bzip2 compression (which is the default for x86/x86_64 <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bzImage</code> anyway, Buildroot handles this).</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Drawbacks of Solution A:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Kernel command line configuration is hidden within a script, not in the central Buildroot configuration.</li>
  <li>Harder to maintain and modify parameters later.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><strong>Solution B: Integrate Script with Buildroot <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> (Recommended)</strong></p>

<p>This approach modifies the script to use the standard <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> variable defined in the defconfig. This is the preferred method for better integration and maintainability.</p>

<p><strong>1. Modify <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh</code>:</strong></p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">--- a/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh
</span><span class="p">@@ -10,8 +10,10 @@</span>
 KERNEL="${BINARIES_DIR}/bzImage"
 INITRD="${BINARIES_DIR}/rootfs-sbnb.cpio"
 OS_RELEASE="${TARGET_DIR}/etc/os-release"
<span class="gd">-CMDLINE="console=tty0 console=ttyS0 earlyprintk verbose intel_iommu=on module_blacklist=nouveau,nvidiafb,snd_hda_intel dyndbg=\"module firmware_class +p; module microcode +p; module ccp +p\""
</span><span class="gi">+# --- MODIFIED KERNEL COMMAND LINE (Read from Buildroot Env) ---
+# Read command line from BR2_CMDLINE environment variable provided by Buildroot.
+CMDLINE="${BR2_CMDLINE:?Error: BR2_CMDLINE environment variable not set or empty. Check Buildroot kernel configuration (BR2_CMDLINE).}"
+# --- END MODIFICATION ---
</span> CMDLINE_TMP=$(mktemp)
 OUTPUT=sbnb.efi
<span class="err">
</span><span class="p">@@ -41,8 +43,13 @@</span>
     --add-section .initrd="${INITRD}" --change-section-vma .initrd=$(printf 0x%x $initrd_offs) \
     "${STUB}" "${OUTPUT}"
<span class="err">
</span><span class="gi">+# Clean up temporary file
+rm -f "${CMDLINE_TMP}"
+
</span> # Output the result
 echo "Output: ${OUTPUT}"
<span class="gi">+
+# Move the final EFI file to the standard Buildroot images directory (BINARIES_DIR=output/images)
+mv "${OUTPUT}" "${BINARIES_DIR}/"
+echo "Moved ${OUTPUT} to ${BINARIES_DIR}/"
</span><span class="err">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Change:</strong> Replaced the hardcoded <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CMDLINE</code> variable with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CMDLINE="${BR2_CMDLINE:?...}"</code>. This reads the command line string from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> environment variable, which Buildroot sets based on the defconfig. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:?Error...</code> part ensures the script fails if <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> isn’t properly set in the configuration, preventing silent errors.</li>
  <li><strong>Added:</strong> Cleanup and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mv</code> command as in Solution A.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Modify <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">configs/sbnb_defconfig</code>:</strong></p>

<p>Define <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> with all required parameters, including <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code>. Also ensure CPIO settings are correct.</p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">--- a/configs/sbnb_defconfig
</span><span class="gi">+++ b/configs/sbnb_defconfig
</span><span class="p">@@ -8,9 +8,9 @@</span>
 BR2_ROOTFS_OVERLAY="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/rootfs-overlay"
 BR2_ROOTFS_PRE_BUILD_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/pre_build.sh"
 BR2_ROOTFS_POST_BUILD_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/post_build.sh"
<span class="gd">-# This post-image script creates a unified EFI executable (sbnb.efi)
-# IMPORTANT: The kernel command line is HARDCODED inside create_efi.sh
-# Standard BR2_KERNEL_CMDLINE_* options will NOT affect sbnb.efi
</span><span class="gi">+# This post-image script creates a unified EFI executable (sbnb.efi).
+# With Solution B, the script reads the command line from BR2_CMDLINE below.
</span> BR2_ROOTFS_POST_IMAGE_SCRIPT="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh"
<span class="gd">-BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_GZIP=y
</span> BR2_LINUX_KERNEL=y
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_USE_CUSTOM_CONFIG=y
 # Switch back to upstream kernel once Restricted Injection hypervisor support
<span class="p">@@ -20,6 +20,8 @@</span>
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_REPO_VERSION="svsm"
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CUSTOM_CONFIG_FILE="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/kernel-config"
 BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="kernel-config-firmware"
<span class="gi">+# Define the kernel command line arguments (used by create_efi.sh in Solution B)
+BR2_CMDLINE="console=tty0 console=ttyS0 earlyprintk verbose intel_iommu=on module_blacklist=nouveau,nvidiafb,snd_hda_intel dyndbg=\"module firmware_class +p; module microcode +p; module ccp +p\" nomodeset"
</span> BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_NEEDS_HOST_LIBELF=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_LINUX_HEADERS_CUSTOM_6_11=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_LINUX_TOOLS_CPUPOWER=y
<span class="p">@@ -75,14 +77,11 @@</span>
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_CURSES=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_HOST_PYTHON3_SSL=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_TAILSCALE=y
<span class="gi">+# Configure CPIO rootfs generation to match the script's expectation
</span> BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO=y
<span class="gd">-# BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_XZ is not set
-BR2_PACKAGE_SEVCTL=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_SNPGUEST=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_TPM2_TOOLS=y
-BR2_PACKAGE_BUSYBOX_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/busybox.fragment"
-BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS=y
-BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS4_XZ=y
</span><span class="gi">+# Ensure CPIO is not compressed as the script uses the base name 'rootfs-sbnb.cpio'
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_NONE=y
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_CPIO_FILENAME="rootfs-sbnb.cpio"
</span> BR2_PACKAGE_OPENVMTOOLS=y
 BR2_SHARED_STATIC_LIBS=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_FATRESIZE=y
<span class="p">@@ -97,4 +96,10 @@</span>
 BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON3_ZLIB=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_PYTHON_REQUESTS=y
 BR2_PACKAGE_JQ=y
<span class="gi">+BR2_PACKAGE_SEVCTL=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_SNPGUEST=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_TPM2_TOOLS=y
+BR2_PACKAGE_BUSYBOX_CONFIG_FRAGMENT_FILES="$(BR2_EXTERNAL_SBNB_PATH)/board/sbnb/sbnb/busybox.fragment"
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS=y
+BR2_TARGET_ROOTFS_SQUASHFS4_XZ=y
</span><span class="err">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Changes:</strong> Added the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code> definition containing the full command string including <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code>. Adjusted comments. Ensured CPIO settings are correct (same as Solution A). Removed <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_LINUX_KERNEL_GZIP=y</code> (same reason as Solution A).</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Benefits of Solution B:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Centralizes kernel command line configuration in the standard Buildroot <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">defconfig</code>.</li>
  <li>Easier to manage and modify parameters using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">make menuconfig</code> (under <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Kernel -&gt; Kernel command line string</code>).</li>
  <li>Aligns with standard Buildroot practices.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><strong>Next Steps (Apply either Solution A or B):</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Apply Changes:</strong> Replace the content of your existing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">board/sbnb/sbnb/scripts/create_efi.sh</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">configs/sbnb_defconfig</code> with the versions from your chosen solution (Solution B is recommended).</li>
  <li><strong>Rebuild:</strong> Navigate to your Buildroot top-level directory in the terminal and run:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>make
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>Buildroot will rebuild the necessary components and execute the post-image script, generating a new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output/images/sbnb.efi</code>.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Deploy:</strong> Copy the updated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output/images/sbnb.efi</code> to your target system’s EFI System Partition (ESP).</li>
  <li><strong>Boot:</strong> Boot your GMKtec G5 from the updated EFI file.</li>
  <li><strong>Verify:</strong> Once the system has booted (even if slowly), log in to a console and run the following command to check if <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> was actually passed to the kernel:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">cat</span> /proc/cmdline
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>Look for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code> within the output string.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Long-Term Alternative:</strong></p>

<p>While outside the scope of simply adding <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nomodeset</code>, you might eventually consider whether the custom <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">create_efi.sh</code> script is strictly necessary. Buildroot has built-in support for generating bootable images using standard bootloaders like GRUB2 or syslinux, which handle kernel parameters through their own configuration files managed by Buildroot based on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BR2_CMDLINE</code>. Migrating to a standard bootloader setup could simplify your build process further, but would require more significant changes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bind Mounting /home/user to /userdata</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/bind-mounting-homeuser-to-userdata/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bind Mounting /home/user to /userdata" /><published>2025-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-02T00:13:17+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/bind-mounting-homeuser-to-userdata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/bind-mounting-homeuser-to-userdata/"><![CDATA[<p>This guide explains how to use mount --bind to make your user’s home directory (/home/user) utilize the storage space on a larger partition mounted at /userdata. This method is transparent to most applications.</p>

<p>While mount --bind is effective, other methods like symbolic links (ln -s /userdata /home/user) or changing the home directory path directly in /etc/passwd (usermod -d /userdata user) exist, each with different implications (e.g., symlinks might not be followed by all applications, usermod -d changes the canonical path). This guide focuses on the mount --bind approach.</p>

<p><strong>Assumptions:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Your username is user. <strong>Replace user with your actual username throughout.</strong></li>
  <li>Your large partition is mounted at /userdata.</li>
  <li>You want the actual home directory data to reside in a directory named /userdata.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>🛑 IMPORTANT PREREQUISITES 🛑</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>BACKUP:</strong> <strong>Before starting, create a complete and verified backup of your /home/user directory.</strong> Mistakes can lead to data loss.</li>
  <li><strong>LOG OUT USER:</strong> The user whose home directory is being moved (user) <strong>must be completely logged out</strong> from all graphical sessions and terminal logins.</li>
  <li><strong>USE TTY / DIFFERENT USER:</strong> Perform these steps from a text console (TTY) or by logging in as a different administrative user (or root). <strong>Do not perform these steps while logged into the graphical session of the user being modified.</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Press Ctrl+Alt+F3 (or F1-F6) to switch to a TTY and log in there as root or another admin user.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Steps:</strong></p>

<p><strong>1. Create the Target Directory on /userdata</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Create the directory on the large partition where the home directory data will actually live.<br />
sudo mkdir -p /userdata</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Set Correct Ownership and Permissions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Ensure the new directory belongs to the correct user and group and has standard home directory permissions (700 allows read/write/execute only for the owner).<br />
# Replace user:user with your actual username and primary groupname<br />
sudo chown user:user /userdata<br />
sudo chmod 700 /userdata</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>3. Copy Data from Old Home to New Location</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Use rsync to copy all files. -a preserves permissions, ownership, timestamps, etc. -X preserves extended attributes, -A preserves ACLs (if used). --info=progress2 shows overall progress. The trailing slashes on the paths are important.<br />
# Replace paths if your username or target dir name is different<br />
sudo rsync -aXA --info=progress2 /home/user/ /userdata/</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This might take time depending on the amount of data.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Verify Copy Integrity (Recommended)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Crucial:</strong> Before modifying the original directory, verify the copy is complete and accurate. Choose one method:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><strong>Method A: diff (Checks for differences)</strong><br />
# This command should ideally produce no output if the copy is identical.<br />
# It might list minor differences in temporary files if run immediately after rsync.<br />
sudo diff -qr /home/user/ /userdata/</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>Method B: rsync Dry Run (Checks what <em>would</em> be copied)</strong><br />
# -n: dry run, -i: itemize changes, -c: checksum (slower but thorough)<br />
# This should ideally report “sending incremental file list” and nothing else.<br />
sudo rsync -naic /home/user/ /userdata/</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Investigate any significant reported differences before proceeding.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>5. Rename the Original Home Directory (Safety Backup)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Rename the original directory. This acts as a temporary backup and frees up the /home/user path for the mount point.<br />
sudo mv /home/user /home/user.bak</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Troubleshooting “Device or resource busy”:</strong> If you get this error, ensure user is fully logged out. Use these commands to find processes still using the old directory:<br />
# Option 1: List open files in the directory<br />
sudo lsof /home/user.bak<br />
# Option 2: List processes using the filesystem/directory<br />
sudo fuser -vm /home/user.bak<br />
# Option 3: General process check for the user<br />
ps aux | grep user</p>

    <p>Identify and terminate any remaining processes belonging to user (e.g., sudo kill &lt;PID&gt;).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>6. Create the Empty Mount Point</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Recreate the original directory path. This empty directory will serve as the mount point.<br />
sudo mkdir /home/user</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>7. Set Ownership of the Empty Mount Point</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Crucial:</strong> Ensure this <em>new, empty</em> /home/user directory has the correct ownership <em>before</em> mounting.<br />
sudo chown user:user /home/user</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>8. Test the Bind Mount Manually</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Perform the bind mount temporarily to check if it works.<br />
sudo mount --bind /userdata /home/user</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>9. Verify the Manual Mount</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Check the contents of /home/user. It should now show the files from /userdata.<br />
ls -la /home/user</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Check the system’s mount list to confirm the bind mount is active.<br />
mount | grep /home/user</p>

    <p>You should see a line like /userdata on /home/user type none (rw,bind).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>10. Make the Bind Mount Persistent (Choose ONE method)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Method A: Using /etc/fstab (Traditional)</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Edit /etc/fstab with a text editor like nano:<br />
sudo nano /etc/fstab</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Add the following line at the end. Use tabs or spaces consistently.<br />
# Bind mount user home directory to userdata partition<br />
/userdata  /home/user  none  bind  0  0</p>
      </li>
      <li><strong>Warning:</strong> If /userdata is not available early during boot (e.g., requires drivers/services not yet started), this /etc/fstab entry might cause boot delays or failures. Systemd mount units (Method B) handle dependencies better. Adding the nofail option (bind,nofail) allows booting even if the mount fails, but /home/user might be empty, potentially preventing login or causing application issues. Use nofail with caution for home directories.</li>
      <li>Save and close the file (Ctrl+O, Enter, Ctrl+X in nano).</li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>Test fstab Entry:</strong><br />
sudo umount /home/user  # Unmount the temporary manual mount<br />
sudo mount -a           # Mount all entries in fstab<br />
mount | grep /home/user # Verify it mounted correctly via fstab</p>

        <p>If mount -a gives errors, double-check your /etc/fstab syntax.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Method B: Using Systemd Mount Unit (Modern, Recommended)</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Systemd handles dependencies better, ensuring /userdata is likely ready before attempting the bind mount.</li>
      <li>
        <p>Create a systemd mount unit file. The filename should reflect the mount point path. Convert slashes (/) to dashes (-) and escape dashes properly. For /home/user, a good name is home-user.mount.<br />
sudo nano /etc/systemd/system/home-user.mount</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Paste the following content into the file, adjusting paths if needed:<br />
[Unit]<br />
Description=Bind mount /home/user to /userdata<br />
RequiresMountsFor=/userdata<br />
After=local-fs.target</p>

        <p>[Mount]<br />
What=/userdata<br />
Where=/home/user<br />
Type=none<br />
Options=bind</p>

        <p>[Install]<br />
WantedBy=local-fs.target</p>

        <ul>
          <li>RequiresMountsFor= helps ensure the source is ready.</li>
          <li>After= and WantedBy= integrate it into the boot process.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Save and close the file.</li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>Enable and Test the Systemd Unit:</strong><br />
sudo umount /home/user  # Unmount the temporary manual mount if still active<br />
# Enable the unit to start on boot and start it now<br />
sudo systemctl enable --now home-user.mount<br />
# Check the status<br />
systemctl status home-user.mount<br />
mount | grep /home/user # Verify it mounted correctly</p>

        <p>If there are errors, check the unit file syntax (systemctl status or journalctl -u home-user.mount might give clues).</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>11. Log In and Test Thoroughly</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Log out from the TTY (exit or logout).</li>
  <li>Switch back to the graphical login screen (e.g., Ctrl+Alt+F1 or Ctrl+Alt+F7).</li>
  <li>Log in as the user user.</li>
  <li>Test various applications (browser, file manager, terminal), check file access, create/delete test files, and ensure everything works as expected.</li>
  <li>Open a terminal within the user’s session and run df -h /home/user. The output should show the disk space statistics for the /userdata partition, confirming the redirection is working.</li>
  <li><strong>Reboot the system</strong> and log in again to ensure the persistent mount (fstab or systemd) works correctly after a full restart.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>12. Clean Up (Optional - Use Caution!)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Only after extensive testing (including reboots)</strong> and confirming everything works perfectly, you can remove the backup directory.</li>
  <li><strong>🛑 Double-check you are deleting the correct directory (.bak)! 🛑</strong><br />
# Perform this from a TTY logged in as root or another admin user<br />
sudo rm -rf /home/user.bak</li>
</ul>

<p>You have now successfully redirected your /home/user directory to use the storage space on /userdata using a persistent bind mount.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="aid&gt;linux" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Code Fixer</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/code-fixer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code Fixer" /><published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-01T14:24:29+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/code-fixer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/code-fixer/"><![CDATA[<section class="code-block-container" role="group" aria-label=" Code Block" data-filename="_code_block.txt" data-code="&lt;prompt&gt;
  &lt;purpose&gt;
    You are a specialized code validator and fixer. Your task is to transform code with errors into fully functional, compliant scripts. Success means identifying and correcting 100% of syntax errors, indentation problems, and formatting issues without changing the intended functionality. You will output only the complete, corrected code with no explanatory text.
  &lt;/purpose&gt;
  
  &lt;persona&gt;
    You are a meticulous, efficient code expert who focuses exclusively on code correctness and proper formatting. You prioritize making the code work as intended while adhering to code best practices. You communicate through code only, not explanations.
  &lt;/persona&gt;
  
  &lt;context&gt;
      &lt;key_guidelines&gt;
        &lt;guideline&gt;verify indentation level&lt;/guideline&gt;
        &lt;guideline&gt;UTF-8 file encoding&lt;/guideline&gt;
      &lt;/key_guidelines&gt;
    &lt;error_categories&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Syntax errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Missing colons after function/class declarations or control flow statements&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Unclosed parentheses, brackets, quotes&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Invalid assignment operators&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect function calls&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Indentation errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Inconsistent indentation levels&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Mixing tabs and spaces&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect block indentation&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Format errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Improper spacing around operators&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect line breaks&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Non-compliant naming conventions&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Reference errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Undefined variables&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect attribute references&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Improper function calls&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
    &lt;/error_categories&gt;
  &lt;/context&gt;
  
  &lt;constraints&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Preserve the original code&#39;s intended functionality and logic.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Maintain all meaningful comments from the original code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not add explanatory comments about fixes made.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not use placeholders in the output.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not include any text before or after the fixed code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not explain your changes or reasoning; output only the corrected code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;When multiple valid fixes exist, choose the most codeic approach per PEP 8.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;All syntax errors must be fixed, even if minimal.&lt;/constraint&gt;
  &lt;/constraints&gt;
  
  &lt;instructions&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Think step-by-step about each part of the code script in [[code_script]].&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;First, scan the entire script to identify all error types present.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Fix syntax errors by adding missing colons, parentheses, quotes, and other required syntax elements.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Correct indentation by ensuring consistent use of indentation and proper nesting of code blocks.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Fix variable reference errors by ensuring all variables are properly defined and used.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Correct import statements by fixing their format and order.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Verify function calls to ensure they use parentheses correctly.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Check class definitions for proper syntax and indentation.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Ensure list, dictionary, and set literals are properly formatted.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Verify string formatting and concatenation operations.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;After making all corrections, review the entire script once more to ensure no errors remain.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Return ONLY the complete, corrected code script.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;meta_instruction&gt;For each line of code, ask: &quot;Is this correct code syntax?&quot;&lt;/meta_instruction&gt;
    &lt;meta_instruction&gt;After each fix, mentally verify that the code&#39;s functionality remains unchanged.&lt;/meta_instruction&gt;
  &lt;/instructions&gt;
  
  &lt;input_data&gt;
    &lt;code_script&gt;
```
[[code_script]]
```
    &lt;/code_script&gt;
  &lt;/input_data&gt;
  
  &lt;output_format_specification&gt;
    &lt;format&gt;Complete, working code script with all errors fixed&lt;/format&gt;
    &lt;rules&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Output must start directly with the code (no introductory text)&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Output must end with the code code (no concluding remarks)&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Preserve original docstrings and comments&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Use consistent quotation marks throughout&lt;/rule&gt;
    &lt;/rules&gt;
  &lt;/output_format_specification&gt;

  &lt;evaluation_criteria&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;All syntax errors are fixed (100% required)&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;All indentation errors are fixed (100% required)&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;Code functionality is preserved&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;Output contains only the corrected code&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;No explanation or commentary is included&lt;/criterion&gt;
  &lt;/evaluation_criteria&gt;
  
  &lt;testing_methodology&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Run the corrected script to verify it executes without syntax errors&lt;/test&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Compare input/output behavior of original intent with corrected script&lt;/test&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Check edge cases (empty functions, complex nested structures)&lt;/test&gt;
  &lt;/testing_methodology&gt;
&lt;/prompt&gt;" data-download-link="" data-download-label="Download ">
  <code class="language-">&lt;prompt&gt;
  &lt;purpose&gt;
    You are a specialized code validator and fixer. Your task is to transform code with errors into fully functional, compliant scripts. Success means identifying and correcting 100% of syntax errors, indentation problems, and formatting issues without changing the intended functionality. You will output only the complete, corrected code with no explanatory text.
  &lt;/purpose&gt;
  
  &lt;persona&gt;
    You are a meticulous, efficient code expert who focuses exclusively on code correctness and proper formatting. You prioritize making the code work as intended while adhering to code best practices. You communicate through code only, not explanations.
  &lt;/persona&gt;
  
  &lt;context&gt;
      &lt;key_guidelines&gt;
        &lt;guideline&gt;verify indentation level&lt;/guideline&gt;
        &lt;guideline&gt;UTF-8 file encoding&lt;/guideline&gt;
      &lt;/key_guidelines&gt;
    &lt;error_categories&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Syntax errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Missing colons after function/class declarations or control flow statements&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Unclosed parentheses, brackets, quotes&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Invalid assignment operators&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect function calls&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Indentation errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Inconsistent indentation levels&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Mixing tabs and spaces&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect block indentation&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Format errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Improper spacing around operators&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect line breaks&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Non-compliant naming conventions&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Reference errors&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;examples&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Undefined variables&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Incorrect attribute references&lt;/example&gt;
          &lt;example&gt;Improper function calls&lt;/example&gt;
        &lt;/examples&gt;
      &lt;/category&gt;
    &lt;/error_categories&gt;
  &lt;/context&gt;
  
  &lt;constraints&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Preserve the original code&#39;s intended functionality and logic.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Maintain all meaningful comments from the original code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not add explanatory comments about fixes made.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not use placeholders in the output.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not include any text before or after the fixed code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;Do not explain your changes or reasoning; output only the corrected code.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;When multiple valid fixes exist, choose the most codeic approach per PEP 8.&lt;/constraint&gt;
    &lt;constraint&gt;All syntax errors must be fixed, even if minimal.&lt;/constraint&gt;
  &lt;/constraints&gt;
  
  &lt;instructions&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Think step-by-step about each part of the code script in [[code_script]].&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;First, scan the entire script to identify all error types present.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Fix syntax errors by adding missing colons, parentheses, quotes, and other required syntax elements.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Correct indentation by ensuring consistent use of indentation and proper nesting of code blocks.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Fix variable reference errors by ensuring all variables are properly defined and used.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Correct import statements by fixing their format and order.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Verify function calls to ensure they use parentheses correctly.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Check class definitions for proper syntax and indentation.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Ensure list, dictionary, and set literals are properly formatted.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Verify string formatting and concatenation operations.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;After making all corrections, review the entire script once more to ensure no errors remain.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction&gt;Return ONLY the complete, corrected code script.&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;meta_instruction&gt;For each line of code, ask: &quot;Is this correct code syntax?&quot;&lt;/meta_instruction&gt;
    &lt;meta_instruction&gt;After each fix, mentally verify that the code&#39;s functionality remains unchanged.&lt;/meta_instruction&gt;
  &lt;/instructions&gt;
  
  &lt;input_data&gt;
    &lt;code_script&gt;
```
[[code_script]]
```
    &lt;/code_script&gt;
  &lt;/input_data&gt;
  
  &lt;output_format_specification&gt;
    &lt;format&gt;Complete, working code script with all errors fixed&lt;/format&gt;
    &lt;rules&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Output must start directly with the code (no introductory text)&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Output must end with the code code (no concluding remarks)&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Preserve original docstrings and comments&lt;/rule&gt;
      &lt;rule&gt;Use consistent quotation marks throughout&lt;/rule&gt;
    &lt;/rules&gt;
  &lt;/output_format_specification&gt;

  &lt;evaluation_criteria&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;All syntax errors are fixed (100% required)&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;All indentation errors are fixed (100% required)&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;Code functionality is preserved&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;Output contains only the corrected code&lt;/criterion&gt;
    &lt;criterion&gt;No explanation or commentary is included&lt;/criterion&gt;
  &lt;/evaluation_criteria&gt;
  
  &lt;testing_methodology&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Run the corrected script to verify it executes without syntax errors&lt;/test&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Compare input/output behavior of original intent with corrected script&lt;/test&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;Check edge cases (empty functions, complex nested structures)&lt;/test&gt;
  &lt;/testing_methodology&gt;
&lt;/prompt&gt;</code>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI&gt;prompt" /></entry><entry><title type="html">4-node NethServer 8 homelab</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/4-node-nethserver-8-homelab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4-node NethServer 8 homelab" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T10:34:34+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/4-node-nethserver-8-homelab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/4-node-nethserver-8-homelab/"><![CDATA[<p>NethServer 8 (NS8) marks a significant evolution from its predecessors, embracing a modern <strong>Container Orchestrator</strong> architecture. Instead of a monolithic system, NS8 focuses on managing containerized Apps, offering flexibility but requiring a different deployment mindset compared to NethServer 7 (NS7).</p>

<p>This guide provides a practical example of deploying a multi-node NS8 environment based on community discussions and official documentation (particularly the NS7 vs NS8 comparison [1], which users should note was marked “Work In Progress” and details may evolve). It outlines a 4-node setup designed to separate core services for clarity and potential scalability, using only features and concepts described in the source material.</p>

<p><strong>Key Architectural Concepts &amp; Assumptions (Based on Provided Sources):</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>NS8 Architecture:</strong> NethServer 8 operates primarily as a <strong>Container Orchestrator</strong>. Most core services and third-party applications run as containerized <strong>Apps</strong>. NS8’s main role is managing the lifecycle and configuration of these Apps [1].</li>
  <li><strong>NethSecurity Role:</strong> Advanced gateway and firewall features (like complex rules, Quality of Service (QoS), network zones, integrated VPN servers with account provider integration, Multi-WAN) are <em>not</em> part of NS8’s core. These functions are handled by the separate <strong>NethSecurity</strong> project (<a href="https://nethsecurity.org/">https://nethsecurity.org/</a>) [1]. This guide assumes NethSecurity is <strong>not</strong> deployed unless explicitly mentioned.</li>
  <li><strong>Operating System:</strong> This guide assumes <strong>Rocky Linux 9</strong> (or a similar RHEL 9 derivative or Debian 12) as the base OS for all nodes.</li>
  <li><strong>Network:</strong> We assume a simple, flat network topology (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.0/24</code>).</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="node-1-reverse-proxy--host-firewall">Node 1: Reverse Proxy &amp; Host Firewall</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>IP Example:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.10</code></li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Act as the entry point for web traffic using the built-in Traefik reverse proxy, manage basic host-level firewall rules, and potentially host a simple VPN solution.</li>
</ul>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Install Base OS:</strong> Start with a minimal installation of Rocky Linux 9.</li>
  <li><strong>Set Static IP:</strong> Configure a static IP address using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nmtui</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nmcli</code>.
    <ul>
      <li>Example: IP <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.10/24</code>, Gateway <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.1</code>, DNS <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code> (pointing to Node 2 once it’s up) [2].</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Install NS8 Core:</strong> Download and run the official installation script. <strong>Always obtain the current script URL from the official NS8 documentation [3]</strong>. The command format is generally:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Example format - get current URL from docs!</span>
curl &lt;official-install-script-url&gt; | <span class="nb">sudo </span>bash
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Initial Cluster Creation:</strong> Access the web UI at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://192.168.1.10/cluster-admin/</code>. Follow the prompts to <strong>create the initial cluster</strong>. Set the cluster FQDN (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cluster.lab.local</code>), confirm the network CIDR, and set the administrator password [3]. This node becomes the first member of the cluster.</li>
  <li><strong>Configure Host Firewall (Basic):</strong> NS8 uses a <strong>“Minimal: Firewalld”</strong> approach for host protection [1]. Open necessary ports using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">firewall-cmd</code> or the Cockpit interface (usually accessible via <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://&lt;IP&gt;:9090</code>). For web traffic proxied through this node:
    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>firewall-cmd <span class="nt">--add-service</span><span class="o">=</span>http <span class="nt">--permanent</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>firewall-cmd <span class="nt">--add-service</span><span class="o">=</span>https <span class="nt">--permanent</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>firewall-cmd <span class="nt">--reload</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p><em>Note:</em> Remember, complex firewalling requires <strong>NethSecurity</strong> [1].</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Configure Reverse Proxy (Traefik):</strong> NS8 utilizes Traefik, configured primarily via <strong>“HTTP Routes”</strong> defined within the NS8 UI, typically under App settings or a dedicated Proxy section [1, 4]. Routes are automatically managed for most installed NS8 Apps.
<em>Note:</em> Proxying external services (e.g., custom containers, services on other machines) typically requires manual Traefik configuration files (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.yaml</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.toml</code> placed in a designated directory), bypassing the standard NS8 UI management [1]. This is considered an advanced topic.</li>
  <li><strong>Configure VPN (Limited Options):</strong> NS8 Core does not include integrated VPN servers like OpenVPN or WireGuard out-of-the-box. Manual OS-level VPN setups are generally unsupported via the UI [1]. Based on the NS7/NS8 comparison [1], options include:
    <ul>
      <li><strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wg-easy</code> App:</strong> Install this third-party WireGuard App from the Software Center. <em>Limitation:</em> It lacks integration with NS8 Account Providers (users must be managed separately within the app).</li>
      <li><strong>NethSecurity:</strong> Deploying NethSecurity provides robust <strong>OpenVPN Roadwarrior</strong> capabilities fully integrated with account providers.</li>
      <li><strong>(Manual Container):</strong> Advanced users could deploy and manage their own VPN solution in a container, but this falls outside standard NS8 App management.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>—</p>

<h2 id="node-2-active-directory-dns--dhcp">Node 2: Active Directory, DNS &amp; DHCP</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>IP Example:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code></li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Provide Active Directory (AD) authentication services, internal DNS resolution, and optionally DHCP services using NS8 Apps.</li>
</ul>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Install Base OS &amp; Set Static IP:</strong> Follow the same steps as Node 1 (Steps 1 &amp; 2). Set a static IP (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11/24</code>). Initially, point its DNS to your router (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.1</code>) or an external resolver.</li>
  <li><strong>Install NS8 Core:</strong> Follow the same step as Node 1 (Step 3) to install the core components.</li>
  <li><strong>Join Existing Cluster:</strong> Access this node’s web UI at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://192.168.1.11/</code>. Instead of creating a new cluster, choose the option to <strong>join an existing cluster</strong>. You will likely need to provide the address of an existing cluster member (e.g., Node 1’s IP or FQDN) and the cluster administrator credentials set during Node 1’s setup [3].</li>
  <li><strong>Install Account Provider (Active Directory):</strong> From the NS8 Software Center, install the <strong>”Samba Active Directory”</strong> App. During setup, configure your AD domain name (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ad.lab.local</code>) and administrator password [5].
    <ul>
      <li><em>Important Limitations [1]:</em>
        <ul>
          <li>AD Replication: Joining multiple instances of this App for replication <strong>does not automatically synchronize SysVol or Group Policies (GPOs)</strong> between them. This is a significant limitation compared to traditional AD replication and impacts high availability strategies for GPOs and logon scripts. Manual procedures might be required for full redundancy.</li>
          <li>Local OpenLDAP Alternative: If you choose the local OpenLDAP provider instead of AD, be aware it’s typically <strong>not accessible to services outside the NS8 cluster</strong> [1].</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Configure DNS:</strong> DNS resolution for your internal network can be provided by:
    <ul>
      <li>The <strong>”AD Account Provider” App</strong> itself (integrates AD zones automatically).</li>
      <li>A separate <strong>”DNSMasq” App</strong> [1].
Configure clients and other NS8 nodes to use this node’s IP (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code>) for DNS. (Alternatively, NethSecurity also offers DNS services [1]).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Configure DHCP:</strong> If needed, install the <strong>”DNSMasq” App</strong> [1] to provide DHCP services. Configure the DHCP scope, lease times, default gateway (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.1</code>), and DNS server (this node’s IP, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code>) within the App’s UI. Remember to disable any other DHCP server (like on your router) on the network segment. (Alternatively, NethSecurity also offers DHCP services [1]). Consult the specific App’s documentation for detailed configuration steps.</li>
</ol>

<p>—</p>

<h2 id="node-3-file-sharing--collaboration">Node 3: File Sharing &amp; Collaboration</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>IP Example:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.12</code></li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Host Nextcloud for collaboration and standard SMB/CIFS file shares, integrating with the AD on Node 2.</li>
</ul>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Install Base OS &amp; Set Static IP:</strong> Follow Steps 1 &amp; 2 from Node 1. Set a static IP (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.12/24</code>). Configure its DNS to point to Node 2 (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code>).</li>
  <li><strong>Install NS8 Core:</strong> Follow Step 3 from Node 1.</li>
  <li><strong>Join Existing Cluster:</strong> Follow Step 3 from Node 2 to join this node to the cluster.</li>
  <li><strong>Install Nextcloud App:</strong> Install the official <strong>”Nextcloud”</strong> App from the Software Center. During configuration, connect it to the external Active Directory account provider running on Node 2 [6]. In the App’s Proxy settings [4, 6], define the FQDN for accessing Nextcloud (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cloud.lab.local</code>). Ensure a DNS A record exists (on Node 2) pointing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cloud.lab.local</code> to the IP of the Reverse Proxy (Node 1: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.10</code>).
<em>Note:</em> Automatic configuration/discovery for CalDAV and CardDAV clients <strong>is unconfirmed</strong> in the NS8 context according to the comparison document [1]; manual client configuration might be necessary. Consult the Nextcloud App’s documentation for specifics.</li>
  <li><strong>Install File Server App (SMB):</strong> Install the <strong>”File Server”</strong> App to provide SMBv2/v3 shares integrated with the AD account provider [1]. Configure shared folders and permissions through the App’s UI. Consult the specific App’s documentation for detailed configuration steps.
    <ul>
      <li><em>Limitations [1]:</em>
        <ul>
          <li><strong>Recycle Bin:</strong> Enabling the recycle bin feature for shares requires <strong>Command Line Interface (CLI)</strong> configuration. Refer to community guides linked in the source comparison [1].</li>
          <li><strong>Access Control Lists (ACLs):</strong> UI-based permission management is primarily <strong>”limited to a group”</strong>. Applying fine-grained ACLs typically requires using <strong>”3rd-party tools”</strong> on the command line (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">setfacl</code>) [1].</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>—</p>

<h2 id="node-4-business-applications-platform">Node 4: Business Applications Platform</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>IP Example:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.13</code></li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Host various web-based business applications (e.g., Typo3 CMS, Redmine project management) leveraging NS8’s container orchestration capabilities.</li>
</ul>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Install Base OS &amp; Set Static IP:</strong> Follow Steps 1 &amp; 2 from Node 1. Set a static IP (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.13/24</code>). Configure its DNS to point to Node 2 (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code>).</li>
  <li><strong>Install NS8 Core:</strong> Follow Step 3 from Node 1.</li>
  <li><strong>Join Existing Cluster:</strong> Follow Step 3 from Node 2 to join this node to the cluster.</li>
  <li><strong>Install Web Server (LEMP App):</strong> Since NS8 is a <strong>”Container Orchestrator”</strong> [1], you install a containerized web stack as an App. Look for a suitable <strong>”LEMP” App</strong> (Linux, Nginx, MariaDB/MySQL, PHP) or similar stack in the Software Center (this might be from NethForge or other third-party repositories) [1]. <strong>Verify availability and specific features in the Software Center</strong>. Install the chosen App and configure PHP versions, Nginx virtual hosts, database settings, etc., <em>within</em> this App according to its specific documentation [1].</li>
  <li><strong>Deploy Applications:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Place your application code (Typo3, Redmine) into the appropriate web root directory exposed as a volume by the LEMP App.</li>
      <li>Configure databases for your applications within the MariaDB/MySQL instance running inside the LEMP App container.</li>
      <li>Follow the specific documentation for the chosen LEMP App and your applications [1].</li>
      <li><em>Container Focus [1]:</em> For complex applications, deploying them using their official Docker images might be preferable. However, integrating and managing custom containers seamlessly within the NS8 UI/API framework isn’t explicitly detailed in the source material [1] and may require manual Docker/Podman commands or custom orchestration configurations.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Configure SFTP Access (SFTPGo App):</strong> For secure file transfers, install the <strong><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SFTPGo</code> App</strong> [1]. Configure users, permissions, storage backends, and restrictions within the SFTPGo App’s interface for granular control [1]. Consult the specific App’s documentation for detailed configuration steps.</li>
  <li><strong>Configure Firewall (Host):</strong> Only open ports directly on Node 4’s host firewall (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">firewall-cmd</code> or Cockpit) if services need direct external access <em>not</em> going through the Node 1 reverse proxy. Most web traffic should be directed to Node 1.</li>
  <li><strong>Integrate with AD (Manual/App-Specific):</strong> Configure individual applications (e.g., within Typo3’s backend or Redmine’s administration settings) to use LDAP authentication against the Active Directory server on Node 2, if the application supports it. This typically requires providing the LDAP server address (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.11</code>), base DN, and potentially installing LDAP client tools within the application’s container environment.</li>
  <li><strong>Reverse Proxy Access (Configure on Node 1):</strong> On Node 1 (the Reverse Proxy), configure <strong>”HTTP Routes”</strong> [4] via the NS8 UI. Point specific FQDNs (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">typo3.lab.local</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">redmine.lab.local</code>) to the internal services running on Node 4 (e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">http://192.168.1.13:&lt;LEMP_App_Port&gt;</code>). As noted earlier, managing routes for non-NS8 managed containers/services might require manual Traefik configuration [1]. Ensure DNS A records exist (on Node 2) pointing these FQDNs to the IP of Node 1 (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">192.168.1.10</code>).</li>
</ol>

<p>—</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>This multi-node setup illustrates how NethServer 8’s container-based, App-centric architecture can be used to build a modular server environment based on the provided scenario. It leverages specific Apps for core functionalities, relies on Traefik (via HTTP Routes) for proxied access, utilizes minimal host firewalls, and clearly distinguishes its role from the more comprehensive network security features offered by the NethSecurity project. Understanding these architectural differences [1] and the specific limitations noted is key to successfully deploying and managing NS8.</p>

<p>Always refer to the official NethServer 8 documentation and community resources for the latest information, detailed App configurations, and potential updates to features and limitations, especially considering that some source information [1] was marked as work-in-progress.</p>

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<p>[1] NS7 vs NS8 Feature Comparison (Work In Progress): <a href="https://community.nethserver.org/t/wip-ns7-vs-ns8-feature-comparison/23258">https://community.nethserver.org/t/wip-ns7-vs-ns8-feature-comparison/23258</a> <br />
[2] OS Network Setup Documentation: <a href="https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/os_network.html">https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/os_network.html</a> <br />
[3] NS8 Installation Guide: <a href="https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/install.html">https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/install.html</a> <br />
[4] NS8 Proxy App Documentation: <a href="https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/proxy.html">https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/proxy.html</a> <br />
[5] NS8 User Domains Documentation: <a href="https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/user_domains.html">https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/user_domains.html</a> <br />
[6] NS8 Nextcloud App Documentation: <a href="https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/nextcloud.html">https://docs.nethserver.org/projects/ns8/en/latest/nextcloud.html</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">sbnb/scripts/install-linux.sh</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/sbnbscriptsinstall-linuxsh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sbnb/scripts/install-linux.sh" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T08:32:47+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/sbnbscriptsinstall-linuxsh</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/sbnbscriptsinstall-linuxsh/"><![CDATA[<section class="code-block-container" role="group" aria-label="Bash Code Block" data-filename="bash_code_block.sh" data-code="#!/bin/bash

# ==============================================================================
# Sbnb Linux Bootable USB/Disk Creation Script (Local Mode)
# ==============================================================================
#
# Description:
#   This script automates the creation of a bootable Sbnb Linux drive on Linux.
#   It uses an existing &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; disk image file located in the same
#   directory as this script.
#
# Features:
#   - Uses local &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; file (required).
#   - Uses local &#39;sbnb-tskey.txt&#39; file if present (optional Tailscale key).
#   - Prompts for a custom script (&#39;sbnb-cmds.sh&#39;) to run at boot (optional).
#   - Lists all detected disk-like devices for selection.
#   - Performs necessary unmounting before writing.
#   - Writes the image using &#39;dd&#39; with progress display.
#   - Mounts the ESP partition to copy optional files.
#   - Includes robust cleanup via &#39;trap&#39;.
#
# Requirements:
#   - Bash shell
#   - Core utilities: lsblk, grep, sed, awk, mktemp, mount, umount, cp, tee, sync
#   - &#39;sudo&#39; privileges for disk operations (dd, mount, umount, partprobe).
#   - GNU &#39;dd&#39; (for status=progress).
#   - &#39;partprobe&#39; utility (recommended, for partition table re-scan).
#   - &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; file in the same directory as the script.
#
# More info: https://github.com/sbnb-io/sbnb
#
# WARNING: THIS SCRIPT WILL COMPLETELY OVERWRITE THE SELECTED DISK.
#          ALL DATA ON THE SELECTED DISK WILL BE PERMANENTLY LOST.
#          DOUBLE-CHECK YOUR SELECTION BEFORE CONFIRMING.
#
# ==============================================================================

# Exit immediately if a command exits with a non-zero status
set -e

# --- Configuration ---
SBNB_RAW_FILE=&quot;sbnb.raw&quot;
SBNB_TSKEY_FILE=&quot;sbnb-tskey.txt&quot;
SBNB_CMDS_FILE=&quot;sbnb-cmds.sh&quot; # Target name on ESP for custom script

# --- Color Codes ---
RED=&#39;\033[0;31m&#39;
GREEN=&#39;\033[0;32m&#39;
YELLOW=&#39;\033[1;33m&#39;
BLUE=&#39;\033[0;34m&#39;
NC=&#39;\033[0m&#39; # No Color

# --- Helper Functions ---
info() { echo -e &quot;${GREEN}[INFO]${NC} $1&quot;; }
warn() { echo -e &quot;${YELLOW}[WARN]${NC} $1&quot;; }
error() { echo -e &quot;${RED}[ERROR]${NC} $1&quot;; }
prompt() { read -p &quot;$(echo -e &quot;${BLUE}[PROMPT]${NC} $1&quot;)&quot; &quot;$2&quot;; }

# --- Initial Checks ---
info &quot;Starting Sbnb Linux Bootable Drive Creation Script.&quot;

# Check for root privileges (needed for sudo operations)
if [[ $EUID -eq 0 ]]; then
   error &quot;This script should not be run as root. It uses &#39;sudo&#39; where needed.&quot;
   exit 1
fi
if ! command -v sudo &amp;&gt; /dev/null; then
    error &quot;&#39;sudo&#39; command not found. Please install it.&quot;
    exit 1
fi
# Test sudo privileges early
if ! sudo -v; then
    error &quot;Failed to obtain sudo privileges. Please check your sudo configuration.&quot;
    exit 1
fi

# Check for required local sbnb.raw file
SbnbRawPath=&quot;./${SBNB_RAW_FILE}&quot;
if [ ! -r &quot;$SbnbRawPath&quot; ]; then
  error &quot;&#39;$SBNB_RAW_FILE&#39; not found or not readable in the current directory (${PWD}).&quot;
  exit 1
fi
info &quot;Found required file: $SbnbRawPath&quot;

# Check for optional local sbnb-tskey.txt file
localTsKeyPath=&quot;./${SBNB_TSKEY_FILE}&quot;
if [ -r &quot;$localTsKeyPath&quot; ]; then
  info &quot;Found optional Tailscale key file: $localTsKeyPath&quot;
  useLocalTsKey=true
else
  warn &quot;Optional Tailscale key file (&#39;$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&#39;) not found or not readable. Skipping.&quot;
  useLocalTsKey=false
fi

# --- Disk Selection ---
info &quot;Enumerating available block devices (disks, USB drives, etc.)...&quot;
# Use lsblk: -d (devices only), -p (full paths), -o (columns), -n (no header)
# Filter for type &#39;disk&#39; or &#39;rom&#39;. Exclude loop devices explicitly.
mapfile -t devices &lt; &lt;(lsblk -dpno NAME,SIZE,MODEL,TYPE | grep -E &#39;disk|rom&#39; | grep -v &#39;loop&#39;)

if [ ${#devices[@]} -eq 0 ]; then
    error &quot;No suitable disk devices found.&quot;
    exit 1
fi

echo -e &quot;${YELLOW}Available Devices:${NC}&quot;
echo &quot;--------------------------------------------------&quot;
for i in &quot;${!devices[@]}&quot;; do
  printf &quot;%3d) %s\n&quot; $((i+1)) &quot;${devices[$i]}&quot;
done
echo &quot;--------------------------------------------------&quot;

selectedDiskIndex=&quot;&quot;
while true; do
    prompt &quot;Enter the index number of the target device: &quot; selectedDiskIndex
    if [[ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; =~ ^[0-9]+$ ]] &amp;&amp; [ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; -ge 1 ] &amp;&amp; [ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; -le ${#devices[@]} ]; then
        selectedDrive=$(echo &quot;${devices[$((selectedDiskIndex-1))]}&quot; | awk &#39;{print $1}&#39;)
        info &quot;You selected index $selectedDiskIndex: $selectedDrive&quot;
        break
    else
        warn &quot;Invalid input. Please enter a number between 1 and ${#devices[@]}.&quot;
    fi
done

# --- Confirmation ---
echo -e &quot;${RED}====================== WARNING ======================${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}You have selected device: $selectedDrive${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}ALL DATA ON THIS DEVICE WILL BE PERMANENTLY DESTROYED!${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}=====================================================${NC}&quot;
prompt &quot;Are you absolutely sure you want to proceed? (yes/no): &quot; confirmation
if [[ &quot;$confirmation&quot; != &quot;yes&quot; ]]; then
  error &quot;Operation cancelled by user.&quot;
  exit 1
fi

# --- Unmount Partitions ---
info &quot;Checking for and unmounting partitions on $selectedDrive...&quot;
# Use lsblk -lnpo NAME to get full paths of partitions, suppress errors if none exist
mounted_count=0
for partition_path in $(lsblk -lnpo NAME &quot;$selectedDrive&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || true); do
    # Check if the partition is currently mounted
    if mount | grep -q &quot;^$partition_path &quot;; then # Check for exact match followed by space
        info &quot;Unmounting partition $partition_path...&quot;
        sudo umount &quot;$partition_path&quot;
        mounted_count=$((mounted_count + 1))
    fi
done
if [ $mounted_count -gt 0 ]; then
    info &quot;Finished unmounting partitions.&quot;
else
    info &quot;No mounted partitions found on $selectedDrive.&quot;
fi

# --- Write Image ---
info &quot;Writing &#39;$SBNB_RAW_FILE&#39; to $selectedDrive...&quot;
warn &quot;This may take a while. Please wait...&quot;
# Use bs=4M (often faster), status=progress (GNU dd), conv=fsync (sync data+metadata at end)
if ! sudo dd if=&quot;$SbnbRawPath&quot; of=&quot;$selectedDrive&quot; bs=4M status=progress conv=fsync; then
    error &quot;Failed to write image to $selectedDrive using dd.&quot;
    exit 1
fi
info &quot;Image write completed successfully.&quot;

# --- Partition Recognition ---
info &quot;Ensuring partition table is recognized...&quot;
sync # Ensure all buffers are flushed
# Attempt to re-read partition table. partprobe is common.
if command -v partprobe &amp;&gt; /dev/null; then
    info &quot;Running &#39;partprobe&#39; to update partition table...&quot;
    sudo partprobe &quot;$selectedDrive&quot; || warn &quot;&#39;partprobe&#39; failed, but continuing...&quot;
else
    warn &quot;&#39;partprobe&#39; command not found. The system might take longer to recognize partitions.&quot;
fi
sleep 3 # Give the system a moment

# --- Mount ESP Partition ---
info &quot;Attempting to identify and mount the first partition (ESP)...&quot;
# Determine expected partition name (handles common schemes like sda1, nvme0n1p1, mmcblk0p1)
firstPartition=&quot;&quot;
# Check for pattern like /dev/sda1, /dev/hda1
if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot; ]; then
    firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot;
# Check for pattern like /dev/nvme0n1p1, /dev/mmcblk0p1
elif [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot; ]; then
    firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot;
else
    # Poll briefly in case detection was slow
    warn &quot;First partition not immediately found, polling for 5 seconds...&quot;
    found=false
    for _ in {1..5}; do
        sleep 1
        if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot; ]; then firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot;; found=true; break; fi
        if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot; ]; then firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot;; found=true; break; fi
    done
    if ! $found; then
        error &quot;Could not find the first partition device node (${selectedDrive}1 or ${selectedDrive}p1).&quot;
        error &quot;Cannot proceed with copying files to ESP.&quot;
        exit 1
    fi
fi
info &quot;Identified first partition as: $firstPartition&quot;

# Create temporary mount point
tempMountDir=$(mktemp -d -t sbnb-esp-XXXXXX)

# Setup trap for cleanup BEFORE attempting mount
trap &#39;cleanup&#39; EXIT HUP INT TERM
cleanup() {
    info &quot;Cleaning up...&quot;
    # Check if mount point exists and is mounted before trying to unmount
    if [ -d &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; ] &amp;&amp; mountpoint -q &quot;$tempMountDir&quot;; then
        sudo umount &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || warn &quot;Failed to unmount $tempMountDir during cleanup.&quot;
    fi
    if [ -d &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; ]; then
        rmdir &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || warn &quot;Failed to remove temporary directory $tempMountDir during cleanup.&quot;
    fi
}

# Mount the partition
info &quot;Mounting $firstPartition to $tempMountDir...&quot;
if ! sudo mount &quot;$firstPartition&quot; &quot;$tempMountDir&quot;; then
    error &quot;Failed to mount ESP partition $firstPartition at $tempMountDir.&quot;
    # Trap will handle cleanup
    exit 1
fi
info &quot;ESP partition successfully mounted at $tempMountDir&quot;
espPath=&quot;$tempMountDir&quot;

# --- Copy Files to ESP ---

# Copy Tailscale key if local file exists
if [ &quot;$useLocalTsKey&quot; = true ]; then
  targetTsKeyPath=&quot;$espPath/$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&quot;
  info &quot;Copying local &#39;$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&#39; to $targetTsKeyPath...&quot;
  if ! sudo cp &quot;$localTsKeyPath&quot; &quot;$targetTsKeyPath&quot;; then
      error &quot;Failed to copy Tailscale key to ESP.&quot;
      # Trap will handle cleanup
      exit 1
  fi
  # Note: FAT32 doesn&#39;t store standard Linux permissions well. Ownership/perms might not be critical here.
  info &quot;Tailscale key copied successfully.&quot;
fi

# Ask for and copy custom script if provided
customScriptPath=&quot;&quot;
prompt &quot;Enter path to custom script file (optional, saved as &#39;$SBNB_CMDS_FILE&#39; on drive, runs at boot) [Press Enter to skip]: &quot; customScriptPath

if [ -n &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ]; then
  if [ -f &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ] &amp;&amp; [ -r &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ]; then
    targetScriptPath=&quot;$espPath/$SBNB_CMDS_FILE&quot;
    info &quot;Copying custom script &#39;$customScriptPath&#39; to $targetScriptPath...&quot;
    if ! sudo cp &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; &quot;$targetScriptPath&quot;; then
        error &quot;Failed to copy custom script to ESP.&quot;
        # Trap will handle cleanup
        exit 1
    fi
    # Optional: Make executable if needed, though FAT32 might ignore it. Boot process might source it instead.
    # sudo chmod +x &quot;$targetScriptPath&quot;
    info &quot;Custom script copied successfully.&quot;
  else
    warn &quot;Custom script file &#39;$customScriptPath&#39; not found or not readable. Skipping.&quot;
  fi
else
  info &quot;No custom script path provided. Skipping.&quot;
fi

# --- Final Steps ---
info &quot;File copying complete.&quot;
# Unmounting and cleanup is handled by the trap on exit

echo -e &quot;${BLUE}=========================================${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} Operation completed successfully! ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} You can now safely remove the device: $selectedDrive ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} Remember to adjust BIOS/UEFI settings to boot from it. ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${BLUE}=========================================${NC}&quot;

# Explicitly disable trap before normal exit to avoid double cleanup message
trap - EXIT HUP INT TERM
cleanup # Perform cleanup explicitly on successful exit

exit 0" data-download-link="" data-download-label="Download Bash">
  <code class="language-bash">#!/bin/bash

# ==============================================================================
# Sbnb Linux Bootable USB/Disk Creation Script (Local Mode)
# ==============================================================================
#
# Description:
#   This script automates the creation of a bootable Sbnb Linux drive on Linux.
#   It uses an existing &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; disk image file located in the same
#   directory as this script.
#
# Features:
#   - Uses local &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; file (required).
#   - Uses local &#39;sbnb-tskey.txt&#39; file if present (optional Tailscale key).
#   - Prompts for a custom script (&#39;sbnb-cmds.sh&#39;) to run at boot (optional).
#   - Lists all detected disk-like devices for selection.
#   - Performs necessary unmounting before writing.
#   - Writes the image using &#39;dd&#39; with progress display.
#   - Mounts the ESP partition to copy optional files.
#   - Includes robust cleanup via &#39;trap&#39;.
#
# Requirements:
#   - Bash shell
#   - Core utilities: lsblk, grep, sed, awk, mktemp, mount, umount, cp, tee, sync
#   - &#39;sudo&#39; privileges for disk operations (dd, mount, umount, partprobe).
#   - GNU &#39;dd&#39; (for status=progress).
#   - &#39;partprobe&#39; utility (recommended, for partition table re-scan).
#   - &#39;sbnb.raw&#39; file in the same directory as the script.
#
# More info: https://github.com/sbnb-io/sbnb
#
# WARNING: THIS SCRIPT WILL COMPLETELY OVERWRITE THE SELECTED DISK.
#          ALL DATA ON THE SELECTED DISK WILL BE PERMANENTLY LOST.
#          DOUBLE-CHECK YOUR SELECTION BEFORE CONFIRMING.
#
# ==============================================================================

# Exit immediately if a command exits with a non-zero status
set -e

# --- Configuration ---
SBNB_RAW_FILE=&quot;sbnb.raw&quot;
SBNB_TSKEY_FILE=&quot;sbnb-tskey.txt&quot;
SBNB_CMDS_FILE=&quot;sbnb-cmds.sh&quot; # Target name on ESP for custom script

# --- Color Codes ---
RED=&#39;\033[0;31m&#39;
GREEN=&#39;\033[0;32m&#39;
YELLOW=&#39;\033[1;33m&#39;
BLUE=&#39;\033[0;34m&#39;
NC=&#39;\033[0m&#39; # No Color

# --- Helper Functions ---
info() { echo -e &quot;${GREEN}[INFO]${NC} $1&quot;; }
warn() { echo -e &quot;${YELLOW}[WARN]${NC} $1&quot;; }
error() { echo -e &quot;${RED}[ERROR]${NC} $1&quot;; }
prompt() { read -p &quot;$(echo -e &quot;${BLUE}[PROMPT]${NC} $1&quot;)&quot; &quot;$2&quot;; }

# --- Initial Checks ---
info &quot;Starting Sbnb Linux Bootable Drive Creation Script.&quot;

# Check for root privileges (needed for sudo operations)
if [[ $EUID -eq 0 ]]; then
   error &quot;This script should not be run as root. It uses &#39;sudo&#39; where needed.&quot;
   exit 1
fi
if ! command -v sudo &amp;&gt; /dev/null; then
    error &quot;&#39;sudo&#39; command not found. Please install it.&quot;
    exit 1
fi
# Test sudo privileges early
if ! sudo -v; then
    error &quot;Failed to obtain sudo privileges. Please check your sudo configuration.&quot;
    exit 1
fi

# Check for required local sbnb.raw file
SbnbRawPath=&quot;./${SBNB_RAW_FILE}&quot;
if [ ! -r &quot;$SbnbRawPath&quot; ]; then
  error &quot;&#39;$SBNB_RAW_FILE&#39; not found or not readable in the current directory (${PWD}).&quot;
  exit 1
fi
info &quot;Found required file: $SbnbRawPath&quot;

# Check for optional local sbnb-tskey.txt file
localTsKeyPath=&quot;./${SBNB_TSKEY_FILE}&quot;
if [ -r &quot;$localTsKeyPath&quot; ]; then
  info &quot;Found optional Tailscale key file: $localTsKeyPath&quot;
  useLocalTsKey=true
else
  warn &quot;Optional Tailscale key file (&#39;$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&#39;) not found or not readable. Skipping.&quot;
  useLocalTsKey=false
fi

# --- Disk Selection ---
info &quot;Enumerating available block devices (disks, USB drives, etc.)...&quot;
# Use lsblk: -d (devices only), -p (full paths), -o (columns), -n (no header)
# Filter for type &#39;disk&#39; or &#39;rom&#39;. Exclude loop devices explicitly.
mapfile -t devices &lt; &lt;(lsblk -dpno NAME,SIZE,MODEL,TYPE | grep -E &#39;disk|rom&#39; | grep -v &#39;loop&#39;)

if [ ${#devices[@]} -eq 0 ]; then
    error &quot;No suitable disk devices found.&quot;
    exit 1
fi

echo -e &quot;${YELLOW}Available Devices:${NC}&quot;
echo &quot;--------------------------------------------------&quot;
for i in &quot;${!devices[@]}&quot;; do
  printf &quot;%3d) %s\n&quot; $((i+1)) &quot;${devices[$i]}&quot;
done
echo &quot;--------------------------------------------------&quot;

selectedDiskIndex=&quot;&quot;
while true; do
    prompt &quot;Enter the index number of the target device: &quot; selectedDiskIndex
    if [[ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; =~ ^[0-9]+$ ]] &amp;&amp; [ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; -ge 1 ] &amp;&amp; [ &quot;$selectedDiskIndex&quot; -le ${#devices[@]} ]; then
        selectedDrive=$(echo &quot;${devices[$((selectedDiskIndex-1))]}&quot; | awk &#39;{print $1}&#39;)
        info &quot;You selected index $selectedDiskIndex: $selectedDrive&quot;
        break
    else
        warn &quot;Invalid input. Please enter a number between 1 and ${#devices[@]}.&quot;
    fi
done

# --- Confirmation ---
echo -e &quot;${RED}====================== WARNING ======================${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}You have selected device: $selectedDrive${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}ALL DATA ON THIS DEVICE WILL BE PERMANENTLY DESTROYED!${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${RED}=====================================================${NC}&quot;
prompt &quot;Are you absolutely sure you want to proceed? (yes/no): &quot; confirmation
if [[ &quot;$confirmation&quot; != &quot;yes&quot; ]]; then
  error &quot;Operation cancelled by user.&quot;
  exit 1
fi

# --- Unmount Partitions ---
info &quot;Checking for and unmounting partitions on $selectedDrive...&quot;
# Use lsblk -lnpo NAME to get full paths of partitions, suppress errors if none exist
mounted_count=0
for partition_path in $(lsblk -lnpo NAME &quot;$selectedDrive&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || true); do
    # Check if the partition is currently mounted
    if mount | grep -q &quot;^$partition_path &quot;; then # Check for exact match followed by space
        info &quot;Unmounting partition $partition_path...&quot;
        sudo umount &quot;$partition_path&quot;
        mounted_count=$((mounted_count + 1))
    fi
done
if [ $mounted_count -gt 0 ]; then
    info &quot;Finished unmounting partitions.&quot;
else
    info &quot;No mounted partitions found on $selectedDrive.&quot;
fi

# --- Write Image ---
info &quot;Writing &#39;$SBNB_RAW_FILE&#39; to $selectedDrive...&quot;
warn &quot;This may take a while. Please wait...&quot;
# Use bs=4M (often faster), status=progress (GNU dd), conv=fsync (sync data+metadata at end)
if ! sudo dd if=&quot;$SbnbRawPath&quot; of=&quot;$selectedDrive&quot; bs=4M status=progress conv=fsync; then
    error &quot;Failed to write image to $selectedDrive using dd.&quot;
    exit 1
fi
info &quot;Image write completed successfully.&quot;

# --- Partition Recognition ---
info &quot;Ensuring partition table is recognized...&quot;
sync # Ensure all buffers are flushed
# Attempt to re-read partition table. partprobe is common.
if command -v partprobe &amp;&gt; /dev/null; then
    info &quot;Running &#39;partprobe&#39; to update partition table...&quot;
    sudo partprobe &quot;$selectedDrive&quot; || warn &quot;&#39;partprobe&#39; failed, but continuing...&quot;
else
    warn &quot;&#39;partprobe&#39; command not found. The system might take longer to recognize partitions.&quot;
fi
sleep 3 # Give the system a moment

# --- Mount ESP Partition ---
info &quot;Attempting to identify and mount the first partition (ESP)...&quot;
# Determine expected partition name (handles common schemes like sda1, nvme0n1p1, mmcblk0p1)
firstPartition=&quot;&quot;
# Check for pattern like /dev/sda1, /dev/hda1
if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot; ]; then
    firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot;
# Check for pattern like /dev/nvme0n1p1, /dev/mmcblk0p1
elif [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot; ]; then
    firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot;
else
    # Poll briefly in case detection was slow
    warn &quot;First partition not immediately found, polling for 5 seconds...&quot;
    found=false
    for _ in {1..5}; do
        sleep 1
        if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot; ]; then firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}1&quot;; found=true; break; fi
        if [ -b &quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot; ]; then firstPartition=&quot;${selectedDrive}p1&quot;; found=true; break; fi
    done
    if ! $found; then
        error &quot;Could not find the first partition device node (${selectedDrive}1 or ${selectedDrive}p1).&quot;
        error &quot;Cannot proceed with copying files to ESP.&quot;
        exit 1
    fi
fi
info &quot;Identified first partition as: $firstPartition&quot;

# Create temporary mount point
tempMountDir=$(mktemp -d -t sbnb-esp-XXXXXX)

# Setup trap for cleanup BEFORE attempting mount
trap &#39;cleanup&#39; EXIT HUP INT TERM
cleanup() {
    info &quot;Cleaning up...&quot;
    # Check if mount point exists and is mounted before trying to unmount
    if [ -d &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; ] &amp;&amp; mountpoint -q &quot;$tempMountDir&quot;; then
        sudo umount &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || warn &quot;Failed to unmount $tempMountDir during cleanup.&quot;
    fi
    if [ -d &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; ]; then
        rmdir &quot;$tempMountDir&quot; 2&gt;/dev/null || warn &quot;Failed to remove temporary directory $tempMountDir during cleanup.&quot;
    fi
}

# Mount the partition
info &quot;Mounting $firstPartition to $tempMountDir...&quot;
if ! sudo mount &quot;$firstPartition&quot; &quot;$tempMountDir&quot;; then
    error &quot;Failed to mount ESP partition $firstPartition at $tempMountDir.&quot;
    # Trap will handle cleanup
    exit 1
fi
info &quot;ESP partition successfully mounted at $tempMountDir&quot;
espPath=&quot;$tempMountDir&quot;

# --- Copy Files to ESP ---

# Copy Tailscale key if local file exists
if [ &quot;$useLocalTsKey&quot; = true ]; then
  targetTsKeyPath=&quot;$espPath/$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&quot;
  info &quot;Copying local &#39;$SBNB_TSKEY_FILE&#39; to $targetTsKeyPath...&quot;
  if ! sudo cp &quot;$localTsKeyPath&quot; &quot;$targetTsKeyPath&quot;; then
      error &quot;Failed to copy Tailscale key to ESP.&quot;
      # Trap will handle cleanup
      exit 1
  fi
  # Note: FAT32 doesn&#39;t store standard Linux permissions well. Ownership/perms might not be critical here.
  info &quot;Tailscale key copied successfully.&quot;
fi

# Ask for and copy custom script if provided
customScriptPath=&quot;&quot;
prompt &quot;Enter path to custom script file (optional, saved as &#39;$SBNB_CMDS_FILE&#39; on drive, runs at boot) [Press Enter to skip]: &quot; customScriptPath

if [ -n &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ]; then
  if [ -f &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ] &amp;&amp; [ -r &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; ]; then
    targetScriptPath=&quot;$espPath/$SBNB_CMDS_FILE&quot;
    info &quot;Copying custom script &#39;$customScriptPath&#39; to $targetScriptPath...&quot;
    if ! sudo cp &quot;$customScriptPath&quot; &quot;$targetScriptPath&quot;; then
        error &quot;Failed to copy custom script to ESP.&quot;
        # Trap will handle cleanup
        exit 1
    fi
    # Optional: Make executable if needed, though FAT32 might ignore it. Boot process might source it instead.
    # sudo chmod +x &quot;$targetScriptPath&quot;
    info &quot;Custom script copied successfully.&quot;
  else
    warn &quot;Custom script file &#39;$customScriptPath&#39; not found or not readable. Skipping.&quot;
  fi
else
  info &quot;No custom script path provided. Skipping.&quot;
fi

# --- Final Steps ---
info &quot;File copying complete.&quot;
# Unmounting and cleanup is handled by the trap on exit

echo -e &quot;${BLUE}=========================================${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} Operation completed successfully! ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} You can now safely remove the device: $selectedDrive ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${GREEN} Remember to adjust BIOS/UEFI settings to boot from it. ${NC}&quot;
echo -e &quot;${BLUE}=========================================${NC}&quot;

# Explicitly disable trap before normal exit to avoid double cleanup message
trap - EXIT HUP INT TERM
cleanup # Perform cleanup explicitly on successful exit

exit 0</code>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry><entry><title type="html">WinNTSetup - universal Windows Installer</title><link href="https://ib.bsb.br/winntsetup-universal-windows-installer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WinNTSetup - universal Windows Installer" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T10:21:18+00:00</updated><id>https://ib.bsb.br/winntsetup-universal-windows-installer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ib.bsb.br/winntsetup-universal-windows-installer/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Features:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Install (unattend) Windows 2k/XP/20??/Vista/7/8.x/10/11 x86/x64/arm64</li>
  <li>Practically runs even on the most minimalistic WinPE</li>
  <li>selectable drive letter for the new Windows installation</li>
  <li>Fully automated with save/load setting in ini file and various command line options</li>
  <li>Install Windows also if nlite/vlite has remove winnt32.exe/setup.exe</li>
  <li>Integrate Drivers: normal PNP and Textmode Drivers</li>
  <li>Patch uxtheme to allow unsigned Themes</li>
  <li>Some common registry tweaks and *.reg file import</li>
  <li>DISM APPX  removal, feature enable/disable</li>
  <li>Simple VHD creation and Installation</li>
  <li>Support “Windows to Go” for Windows 7 and later installs</li>
  <li>Supports WimBoot and CompactOS option for Windows 7 and later</li>
  <li>Supports all current WIM files: WIM/SWM/ESD and ISO files</li>
  <li>WinCapture - capture a Windows installation to WIM or ESD file</li>
  <li>MinWin - simple trimming WIM in memory before apply</li>
  <li>WinCopy - copy an existing Windows installation to another partition</li>
  <li>Offline Hotfix uninstall</li>
  <li>Offline password reset</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Not Supported:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>- No Windows embedded version (this includes WinFLP)</li>
  <li>- No upgrades of existing installations</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>About driver installation:</strong></p>

<p>Every driver added in NT6.x windows will be added to the driver store.<br />
So it’s not recommended to add countless driver, but rather more really required ones.</p>

<p>NT5.x massstorage driver integration is possible thanks to <strong>Mr dUSHA</strong> powerful <strong>MSSTMake.exe</strong> tool</p>

<p><strong>To the Unattend option:</strong>It’s possible to use an <strong>unattend.xml</strong> to run the Setup unattended.<br />
But as the actual WinPE Setup Phase isn’t effective in that way of install, all Winpe related settings inside the unattend.xml<br />
won’t be applied.</p>

<p><strong>Ini config file</strong>It’s possible to save all GUI-settings to a ini file:</p>

<p>push <strong>Ctrl + S</strong> to <strong>save</strong> all settings to an ini.<br />
push <strong>Ctrl + L</strong> to <strong>load</strong> all settings from an ini.</p>

<p>A <strong>WinNTSetup.ini</strong> file in the same dir as the app itself will be loaded automatically at startup.</p>

<p>It also can be selected via command line:</p>

<p>WinNTSetup.exe /cfg:”C:\mysettings.ini”</p>

<p>If you want to modify ini settings yourself, click-click has made a nice <a href="https://www.mediafire.com/file/znuf574scdac94d/WinNTGUI2Ini.pdf/file">PDF</a> for it.</p>

<p>For advanced users there are also hidden settings described in the included WinNTSetup.ini.txt</p>

<p><strong>Command line:</strong></p>

<p>- Press F1 to get list of all options</p>

<p><strong>To install Windows in a VHD file:</strong>- requires Windows 7 as OS and <strong>Windows 7 Ultimate, Enterprise or Server 2008 R2</strong> as Source<br />
- create a partitioned VHD and assign a drive letter (push Ctrl + Shift + V to use build in diskpart wrapper for this)<br />
- select the VHD drive as installation drive (make sure you boot drive ist a active primary partition on a physical disk)</p>

<p>If you get an Antivirus warning from your AV software, please report it to them as a false positive and let them check it.</p>

<p><strong>Current Version: 5.4.1</strong></p>

<p>Download: <a href="https://mega.nz/folder/ObATya7C#oR2t79bT-4MGjKxOAYwkbQ">Mega</a> - <a href="https://www.mediafire.com/folder/53um6k2nmhvd5/">MediaFire</a></p>

<p><strong>Edited December 29, 2024 by JFX</strong></p>

<p>21</p>

<p><a href="https://msfn.org/board/profile/25215-jaclaz/" title="Go to jaclaz's profile"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/monthly_2017_08/Jgray.thumb.jpg.8353b51d429039be7eaa0a7da3fbd3fe.jpg" alt="Image 4: jaclaz" /></a></p>

<p>It looks like a nice tool. <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_thumbup.gif" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 5: :thumbup" /></a></p>

<p>And it shouldn’t be dedicated to “USB only”, if I am not mistaken. <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_unsure.png" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 6: :unsure:" /></a></p>

<p>Let’s hope that whoever tests it will be so kind as to (please read as “anyone testing it please do”) provide - for the benefit of the less expereinced users - some details on the various available options, and their usage.</p>

<p>Usual bothering request to the developer <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_blushing.gif" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 7: :blushing:" /></a> :</p>

<ul>
  <li>Any chance that it will ever support command line? (or provide a pre-set in the form of a .ini file?) <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_whistling.gif" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 8: :whistle:" /></a></li>
</ul>

<p>jaclaz</p>

<p><a href="https://msfn.org/board/profile/314753-jfx/" title="Go to JFX's profile"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/monthly_2025_01/avatar_small.thumb.png.54db03064974c08ad6356a340b1173b3.png" alt="Image 9: JFX" /></a></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Author</strong></li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>And it shouldn’t be dedicated to “USB only”, if I am not mistaken. <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_unsure.png" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 10: :unsure:" /></a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, you right, not the most correct forum section</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Let’s hope that whoever tests it will be so kind as to (please read as “anyone testing it please do”) provide - for the benefit of the less expereinced users - some details on the various available options, and their usage.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>hmm, yeah i could add tool tip/balloons for every check box</p>

<p>Thanks for reminding about the ini file <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_smile.png" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 11: :)" /></a> Added to first Post</p>

<p>More command line options could be added, if requested.</p>

<ul>
  <li>2 weeks later…</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://msfn.org/board/profile/125656-lama/" title="Go to lama's profile"><img src="blob:http://localhost/3421ba85060e6030e813683c8ff84905" alt="Image 12: lama" /></a></p>

<p>Thanks for the link @ reboot.pro wonko, but, how come this v 2.0 was not even mentioned by original creator? Excuse me but,…Did i missed the part where JFX became “was_JFX” there? <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_huh.png" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 13: :huh:" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://msfn.org/board/profile/25215-jaclaz/" title="Go to jaclaz's profile"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/monthly_2017_08/Jgray.thumb.jpg.8353b51d429039be7eaa0a7da3fbd3fe.jpg" alt="Image 14: jaclaz" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thanks for the link @ reboot.pro wonko, but, how come this v 2.0 was not even mentioned by original creator? Excuse me but,…Did i missed the part where JFX became “was_JFX” there? <a href="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/emoticons/default_huh.png" title="Enlarge image"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/applications/core/interface/js/spacer.png" alt="Image 15: :huh:" /></a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Evidently yes.</p>

<p>And however I don’ t think it is part of your business.</p>

<p>jaclaz</p>

<p><a href="https://msfn.org/board/profile/132150-wimb/" title="Go to wimb's profile"><img src="https://msfn.org/board/uploads/av-132150.jpg" alt="Image 16: wimb" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scratchpad" /></entry></feed>